<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- This is a WordPress eXtended RSS file generated by WordPress as an export of your site. -->
<!-- It contains information about your site's posts, pages, comments, categories, and other content. -->
<!-- You may use this file to transfer that content from one site to another. -->
<!-- This file is not intended to serve as a complete backup of your site. -->

<!-- To import this information into a WordPress site follow these steps: -->
<!-- 1. Log in to that site as an administrator. -->
<!-- 2. Go to Tools: Import in the WordPress admin panel. -->
<!-- 3. Install the "WordPress" importer from the list. -->
<!-- 4. Activate & Run Importer. -->
<!-- 5. Upload this file using the form provided on that page. -->
<!-- 6. You will first be asked to map the authors in this export file to users -->
<!--    on the site. For each author, you may choose to map to an -->
<!--    existing user on the site or to create a new user. -->
<!-- 7. WordPress will then import each of the posts, pages, comments, categories, etc. -->
<!--    contained in this file into your site. -->

<!-- generator="WordPress/3.8" created="2014-01-03 11:14" -->
<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:excerpt="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/excerpt/"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/"
>

<channel>
	<title>Davis Vision Therapy Blog</title>
	<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog</link>
	<description>Just another WordPress site</description>
	<pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2014 11:14:03 +0000</pubDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<wp:wxr_version>1.2</wp:wxr_version>
	<wp:base_site_url>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog</wp:base_site_url>
	<wp:base_blog_url>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog</wp:base_blog_url>

	<wp:author><wp:author_id>1</wp:author_id><wp:author_login>admin</wp:author_login><wp:author_email>dandy_ojeda@geadesigns.com.au</wp:author_email><wp:author_display_name><![CDATA[admin]]></wp:author_display_name><wp:author_first_name><![CDATA[]]></wp:author_first_name><wp:author_last_name><![CDATA[]]></wp:author_last_name></wp:author>


	<generator>http://wordpress.org/?v=3.8</generator>

	<item>
				<title>Our New, Updated site!</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=69</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2011 11:47:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/?p=69</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[We are in the process of making some changes to our site in design and layout, as well as additions such as our new blog.  Please be patient with us as the construction continues.  Thanks!]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>69</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2011-06-09 11:47:25</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2011-06-09 11:47:25</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>our-new-updated-site</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Dr. Davis and Staff Present: Patient Appreciation Day</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=73</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2011 12:47:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/?p=73</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<strong><em>An Appreciation of the Success of Vision Therapy.</em></strong></br>
<strong>FREDERICKSBURG, VA, June 4, 2011</strong> – Dr. Davis and his staff at Developmental Optometry &amp; Vision Therapy Services will be celebrating an appreciation for their patients, past and present, on Saturday, June 4th from 12:00 pm to 3:00 pm at their Fredericksburg office.  Refreshments will be served.<br/><!--more-->
The Patient Appreciation Day is in recognition of the patients that have or are conquering the limitations that vision problems give through vision therapy.  Having seen how vision therapy has opened up the future for many people, the Developmental Optometry team wants to not only hear these success stories, but let their former and current patients share stories among each other in a friendly and casual environment.<br/>
The event is taking place at the Fredericksburg office:  701 Westwood Office Park, Fredericksburg, VA 22401.<br/>
If you are interested in knowing more about vision therapy, or you, your child, or someone you know has unidentified challenges in reading, reading comprehension, school or business work, attention to visual details, or other similar areas, please feel free to attend the event, meet with the staff, and speak directly to patients.<br/>
For more information about the Patient Appreciation Day event, or about vision therapy, please call 703-753-9777 or visit www.davisvisiontherapy.com.<br/>
<strong>About Developmental Optometry &amp; Vision Therapy Services</strong>
Developmental Optometry &amp; Vision Therapy Services, operated under Dr. Tod Davis, is a talented and compassionate staff that specializes in developmental vision care and vision therapy.  Dr. Davis has over 25 years of clinical experience, and is committed to excellent, professional, educated care. Developmental Optometry has three offices, located in Fredericksburg, Gainesville, and Winchester.  Visit DavisVisionTherapy.com for more information.<br/>
Media Contact:
Scot Small
703-229-0825
scot@revbuilders.com]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>73</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2011-06-09 12:47:34</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2011-06-09 12:47:34</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>dr-davis-and-staff-present-patient-appreciation-day</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Educators Find New Hope for Struggling Students</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=84</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2011 08:30:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=84</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<strong><em>Students Can Get Help Before School Starts</em></strong>
<br/><strong>FREDERICKSBURG, Va. Aug. 16, 2011</strong> - This August, as children head back to schools which have reduced budgets, National Children’s Vision & Learning Month takes on new meaning.  Teachers and administrators now need to be more creative in order to help their students succeed.  This may include challenging previous concepts regarding vision and learning.<!--more-->
<br/>Two educators from New Jersey have shed some light on why teachers and administrators across the US are rethinking their model of vision and how it relates to learning.  Many students with attention problems, learning disabilities, and gifted students that don’t achieve to their potential have one thing in common, vision disorders that have contributed to their learning difficulties.
<br/>Nicole Moore, Principal of Indian Mills Elementary School, shares, <em>“As a principal who sits on the intervention services committee, we try to do whatever is possible to stop children from needing to be classified for special education services.  One of the interventions that parents have told me makes a big difference in their children’s ability to read and learn is optometric vision therapy.”</em>
<br/><em>“Our district has one of the lowest rates of student classification for special education in the county,”</em> Moore continues, <em>“I believe screening and remediation of learning-related vision problems have been a significant factor in reducing the number of children referred for special education services.”</em>
<br/>Moore credits Barbara Scola, the Director of Pupil Services, for bringing optometric vision therapy to her school as one of the many interventions necessary to help their students.
<br/>When asked what prompted Scola to consider that vision might be one of the missing links to helping students learn, she recalled, <em>“I was working on my master’s thesis on reading interventions and had the opportunity to work with a student who had excellent comprehension when the material was read to him, but struggled when he tried to read on his own.” </em> 
<br/>As she worked with him she found that he knew his words in isolation, yet when he saw the same words at the beginning of a line in a paragraph he didn’t recognize them because he cut off the first two letters.  For example, <em>“Treat yourself to some ice cream”</em> he would read as <em>“Eat yourself to some ice cream.”</em>  Scola tried teaching him context clues to help it make sense, to force him to go back and look at the beginnings of the words, but it was laborious.
<br/><em>“This was quite a mystery, so I started researching to see what it could be.  I suspected that his vision might be playing a role, so I started searching for information on learning disabilities and vision.  And that’s what lead me to optometric vision therapy,”</em> Scola continued.   
<br/>Following Scola’s recommendation, the mother took her child to an optometrist who had an in-office vision therapy program.  After completing optometric vision therapy, he did very well in school.
<br/>Once Scola received her Master’s Degree in Education Administration, she joined Moore in the Shamong School District as the Director of Pupil Services and began implementing her new strategies. The mother of one of the first children who went through optometric vision therapy was working on her Ph.D. in Reading. Scola had encouraged her to give vision therapy a try, <em>“she did not believe us at all, she thought it was bunk. Even with all of her education she had never heard of it. But her daughter couldn't read, so we said it can't hurt, just try it.”</em> And now her daughter is an avid reader and an excellent student thanks to optometric vision therapy.  
<br/><strong>Some of the most common signs that a pupil may have a learning related vision disorder are:</strong>
<br/>
<ul>
<li>Homework battles even though the child is bright and may do well in school (because their eyes are tired at the end of the day from straining to focus),</li>
	<li>Tilts head or lays head on the desk during reading</li>
	<li>Short attention span when reading</li>
	<li>Poor reading comprehension</li>
	<li>Skips lines, rereads lines.</li>
</ul>
<br/>Moore encourages other principals and administrators to "<em>think outside the box when it comes to learning or reading issues; I had never heard of optometric vision therapy before.  Now we know what to look for in children with possible vision disorders and with vision therapy we have seen significant changes in these children’s’ ability and enjoyment of reading."</em>
<br/>Moore and Scola (now the Director of Special Services at Winslow Schools) were delighted to learn that the American Optometric Association responded to President Obama's call to ensure that no child is left behind in the classroom due to an undetected or untreated eye or vision disorder, by holding a School Readiness Summit in Washington, DC.  The summit's interdisciplinary workgroup - comprising nearly 50 leaders in their respective fields - documented and recognized the established link between healthy vision and classroom learning.
<br/>As a result of this Summit, the American Federation of Teachers issued the following statement: <em>“Even the most gifted students will struggle academically if they have trouble seeing the blackboard or focusing on a book. A tremendous amount of learning happens visually, so proper vision care is crucial to helping students reach their full potential.”</em>
<br/>Scola explains to parents, <em>“It doesn’t matter if your child is gifted or not, if vision isn’t working right, your eyes don’t send the right signals to your brain.  It’s like having a real high speed computer, but if the keyboard isn't working, you get the wrong information, if any.”  </em>
<br/>Dr. Tod R. Davis, a developmental optometrist who has an office in Fredericksburg, VA, and who diagnoses and treats vision problems that interfere with academic success says, <em>“I have seen a lot of children from  all over the Prince William County area who struggled with reading before the underlying vision problem was found and treated.  I hope that educators in our area are inspired by what Ms. Scola and Ms. Moore have done in their schools.”</em>
<br/>Dr. Bradley Habermehl, President of the College of Optometrists in Vision Development (COVD) concurs, <em>“We are delighted to see educators, such as Ms. Moore and Ms. Scola, embracing optometric vision therapy.  We receive large numbers of thank you letters from parents who were at their wits end, thanking vision therapy for changing the lives of their children.”</em>
<br/>Please join COVD in this year’s campaign for National Children’s Vision & Learning Month and visit us at www.COVD.org where you can learn about how vision disorders can cause even the brightest children to struggle with learning.
<br/>
<strong>About Developmental Optometry & Vision Therapy Services</strong>
Developmental Optometry & Vision Therapy Services, operated under Dr. Tod Davis, is a talented and compassionate staff that specializes in developmental vision care and vision therapy.  Dr. Davis has over 25 years of clinical experience, and is committed to excellent, professional, educated care. Developmental Optometry has three offices, located in Fredericksburg, Gainesville, and Winchester.  Visit DavisVisionTherapy.com for more information.
<br/><strong>About COVD</strong>
The College of Optometrists in Vision Development (COVD) is an international, non-profit optometric membership organization that provides education, evaluation and board certification programs in behavioral and developmental vision care, vision therapy and visual rehabilitation. The organization is comprised of doctors of optometry, vision therapists and other vision specialists. For more information on learning-related vision problems, vision therapy and COVD, please visit www.covd.org or call 888.268.3770.
CONTACT:  Pamela R. Happ, CAE, COVD Executive Director, 888.268.3770
<br/>####
<br/><strong>Media Contact:</strong>
Scot Small
703-229-0825
scot@revbuilders.com]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>84</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2011-08-16 08:30:29</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2011-08-16 08:30:29</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>educators-find-new-hope-for-struggling-students</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Our New Blog - Up and Running!</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=104</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2011 07:55:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=104</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Exciting news!  We have finally got our new blog up and running!  We hope that what we share will be helpful to you, and if you have any questions or anything you'd like us to talk about, please let us know.  We'd be glad to share!]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>104</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2011-09-07 07:55:59</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2011-09-07 07:55:59</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>new-category-blog</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Success Story of Graham W.</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=111</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2011 15:43:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=111</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA["When we first came to Dr. Davis, we had no idea the problems Graham was having with double vision.  He seemed fine as a young reader, when books had large print and lots of pictures.  Going into the 4th grade, it became more evident that he was having difficulty with comprehension, answering questions, and studying when there was more text to read and smaller print.  Graham was able to maintain good enough grades so his teacher didn’t identify any problems; we became more aware and noticed the issues he was having with homework, and how much he struggled despite working hard.  He failed two SOL’s.<!--more-->
<br/>We decided to get him extra help through a tutor who had been Graham’s first grade teacher.  The teacher’s son had gone through vision therapy and after working just two sessions with Graham, his tutor suggested that Graham have a more thorough eye exam.  The “fix” wasn’t that he needed glasses but his eyes and focusing muscles needed help to work properly.  After the initial test with Dr. Davis, we realized his major problem was that he was seeing double images.
<br/>Once he started vision therapy, he was given a prescription that relaxed his vision and helped him with near work.  He has had amazing success and no longer has double vision.  He’s getting all A’s and B’s, heads straight in to do his homework, no tears, and works through his assignments with less parental intervention.  Graham’s confidence level has increased and he has a more positive outlook.  He passed all 5th grade SOL’s.  We couldn’t be happier with the results!"
<br/><em>-Graham W.'s Parents</em>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[When we first came to Dr. Davis, we had no idea the problems Graham was having with double vision.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>111</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2011-11-03 15:43:08</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2011-11-03 15:43:08</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>success-story-of-graham-w</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Success Story of Gracie V.</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=114</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2011 08:30:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=114</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA["Hello,
<br/>It is my impression that vision therapy is going pretty good so far.  The therapist, Ms. Beth, is great!  She is very personable and relates quite well to Gracie.  Gracie can’t wait to see her every week.
<br/>At first, I thought things were going kind of slow and there were no results to speak of.  But around the end of the second month I started to notice some slight changes with Gracie.  <!--more-->Her eyes seemed more level and a bit straighter when she looked forward.  She also started reading more.  Now we are near the end of the third month and I have noticed she is more outgoing.  During soccer, she participates more and plays harder at the game.  One of the other kid’s parents said to me at the last game that Gracie is playing like a completely different kid compared to last season.  Also, at her first brownie/girl scout troop meeting the other day she hung out with her friends and stood up to contribute in the presentation.  One of the troop leaders said to me that Gracie is really coming along, as she previously kept pretty much to herself when she was in the daisy/girl scout troop which ended this past spring.
<br/>These are all very positive items and I believe are results mainly from her improved vision due to the vision therapy.  I even asked her yesterday if this was the case and she said that yes it was!
<br/>Gracie does not like to speak about her eyesight, even to me.  She still has a long way to go especially with her restricted movement to the left with her left eye and the pulling in of the same eye when she looks down.  However, the initial results are wonderful and I hope and pray that her vision continues to improve with the vision therapy.
<br/>Regarding homework, I think she is ready to move on to the next level.  We will continue to do some of the physical exercises for strength purposes as they are just good things to do in general.
<br/>Thank you so very much for helping Gracie.  I believe her life will be much better because of vision therapy.
<br/>Best regards,
<br/><em>Tom V.</em>"]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[At first, I thought things were going kind of slow and there were no results to speak of.  But around the end of the second month I started to notice some slight changes with Gracie.  Her eyes seemed more level and a bit straighter when she looked forward.  She also started reading more.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>114</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2011-11-07 08:30:23</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2011-11-07 08:30:23</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>success-story-of-gracie-v</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>A Success Story</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=117</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2011 08:00:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=117</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA["We are EXTREMELY pleased with our daughter’s therapy.
<br/>I have had people at our church comment about how she has grown up over the summer and is acting so much more mature.  These people have not been told about her vision therapy.
<br/>Her overall demeanor is very pleasant now.  She used to walk around grouchy and angry almost.  Now you can have a nice conversation with her.<!--more-->
<br/>Homework used to be a chore for her.  I would have to stay on her to do her homework the minute she got home.  Sometimes she would be doing homework at 10pm at night.  Now she comes home and she has already completed it.  I have asked her when does she do her homework.  She said, "Oh, we have extra time at the end of class and I do it then."  Huh?  Is this my daughter we are talking about???
<br/>On top of everything else - her handwriting has improved tremendously.  I used to tell her how messy she wrote and that teachers were not going to let her get by all the time.  Now it is hard to believe it is the same child writing.  Everything is neat and legible.
<br/>Thank you Dr. Davis and all of your therapists for making such a huge difference in not only our daughter's life by our family's life.
<br/>Sincerely,
<br/><em>Mom</em>"]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[We are EXTREMELY pleased with our daughter’s therapy. I have had people at our church comment about how she has grown up over the summer and is acting so much more mature.  These people have not been told about her vision therapy.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>117</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2011-11-10 08:00:01</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2011-11-10 08:00:01</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>a-success-story</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Children’s Wellness Festival</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=124</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2011 18:11:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=124</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[MANASSAS, VA., October 10, 2011 - In order to help combat illness and lack of education for children’s health, the Rotary Clubs of Bull Run, Manassas and Gainesville are announcing the Children’s Wellness Festival, which will take place on Saturday, October 15th at Metz Middle School in Manassas, Va., from 11:00 a.m. to 3:00 p.m.<!--more-->
<br/>The festival, sponsored by the three Rotary Clubs as well as the Manassas City Public Schools Health Advisory Board, focuses on school-age children from Kindergarten through 8th grade. According to Dr. Tod Davis of Developmental Optometry and Vision Therapy Services, the goal is health education. “There will be lots of information at this festival,” Dr. Davis says. “The truth is, there are many fitness and health programs available for young children in the Manassas area—but not everyone knows where to look. Part of the goal of this festival is to make sure that information gets out there so that children are helped.”
<br/>The festival will also feature various activities for children who attend. In addition to information and fun, limited health screenings including height, weight, BMI, hearing, vision and scoliosis will be provided. “We want to make sure that children are getting the information and the care that they need to be healthy,” Dr. Davis adds.
<br/>For more information about the festival, visit Wellness Festival.org.  For more information about Dr. Tod Davis, Developmental Optometry &amp; Vision Therapy Services, visit DavisVisionTherapy.com or call 703-753-9777.
<br/><strong>About Dr. Tod Davis Developmental Optometry &amp; Vision Therapy Services</strong>
Developmental Optometry &amp; Vision Therapy Services, operated under Dr. Tod Davis, is a talented and compassionate staff that specializes in developmental vision care and vision therapy.  Dr. Davis has over 25 years of clinical experience, and is committed to excellent, professional, educated care. Developmental Optometry has three offices, located in Fredericksburg, Gainesville, and Winchester, VA.  Visit DavisVisionTherapy.com for more information.
<br/>Media Contact:
Scot Small
info@revbuilders.com
877-496-5560]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>124</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2011-10-10 18:11:36</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2011-10-10 18:11:36</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>closed</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>children%e2%80%99s-wellness-festival</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Dr. Tod Davis - Press Kit</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=129</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2011 18:25:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=129</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Dr. Tod Davis is the authority on vision therapy in the Washington DC area. Please download the press kit for his biography and select published articles. <a href="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/PDF/DRDAVIS_PressKit.pdf">Download Press Kit</a>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>129</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2011-10-03 18:25:47</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2011-10-03 18:25:47</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>closed</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>dr-tod-davis-press-kit</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Success Story of Mary B.</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=151</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 18:57:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=151</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Mrs. B homeschooled her three children and noticed it took Mary so long to accomplish anything.   Her pace was painfully slow even though she knew the work.  When she was in 8th grade, she asked Mary to choose a book that she liked to read and she chose one that young readers would choose – large font, pictures, basically 4th grade level, and it took her an hour to read 13 pages.<!--more-->
<br/>She brought Mary to Dr. Davis for an evaluation because her eyes were fatigued, they would stop tracking, and due to her slow reading.  Mrs. B. was skeptical at first due to the cost, but also hopeful.  She herself had issues growing up and didn’t want Mary experiencing the same thing so they started her in vision therapy in May 2011.  By June, Mary was keeping her room tidy whereas before you could not find the floor of her room.  It was literally chaos, but now it bothers her for things to be out of order.
<br/>The 9th grade reading list selected by her teacher would have brought her to tears before.  Now she plowed through the books in three weeks in August and comprehended what she had read.  Getting Mary to read is no longer a tug-of-war; no more crying spells or feeling over-whelmed. 
<br/>Mary is so much happier that her eyes are now “working”.  She can sit and do her homework and doesn’t need help.  She has more confidence and is not as clumsy.  Not only have the parents seen the changes and progress, but so has Mary.  Mary enjoyed her sessions, the therapists were fun to work with, and they always treated Mary with great dignity and provided encouragement.  Mrs. B is so grateful and pleased with the outcome of Mary’s vision therapy – “I cannot say thank you enough for all the wonderful changes you’ve helped Mary to achieve.  You are all such a kind, caring group of people and we are blessed to have been patients here.”  And in Mary’s words, “You and your wonderful staff have been such great friends and awesome teachers.  Thanks to you I can now read, do homework quickly and easily without a fit. Thank you sooo much.”]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Mrs. B homeschooled her three children and noticed it took Mary so long to accomplish anything.   Her pace was painfully slow even though she knew the work.  When she was in 8th grade, she asked Mary to choose a book that she liked to read and she chose one that young readers would choose – large font, pictures, basically 4th grade level, and it took her an hour to read 13 pages.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>151</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2011-11-14 18:57:18</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2011-11-14 18:57:18</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>success-story-of-mary-b</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Success Story of Kevin</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=161</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2012 20:40:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=161</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA["The change that I have noticed is the convergence of my eyes. I feel that I can get things completed quicker. My school work has improved, for example, I passed all of my classes for the fall semester and raised my GPA to a 3.2. My lifetime goal of becoming a police officer is now obtainable and I feel confident that I will become a good officer. <!--more-->I have grown even more confident in other things with social life and my sense of humor has increased. I learned about vision therapy in July from auditory therapy and I would recommend vision therapy to anybody that needs it because if it changed my life than it can change yours. I would like to thank Cindy and Tina for the hard work and patience that we put in to get my life on the right track."

<em>by Kevin</em>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[The change that I have noticed is the convergence of my eyes. I feel that I can get things completed quicker.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>161</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-01-24 20:40:20</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-01-24 20:40:20</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>success-story-of-kevin</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Vision Therapy Puts Patient on Track to Realize Career Goals</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=177</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2012 18:40:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=177</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<strong>GAINESVILLE, Va., January 25, 2012 </strong>– Twenty year-old Kevin was beginning to think his dream of becoming a police officer would never happen. He had trouble concentrating on his schoolwork and, even though he studied constantly, couldn’t seem to remember what he’d learned. His grades began to suffer – and so did his hopes of having a career in law enforcement.
<!--more-->
During his search to find a physical reason for his problems, Kevin’s audiologist told him about Dr. Tod Davis and the success he was having with vision therapy. Shortly thereafter, Dr. Davis diagnosed Kevin with convergence insufficiency, a condition in which the eyes fail to work together to focus and transmit messages to the brain. After six months of vision therapy, Kevin is seeing great results.

<em>“My school work has really improved,” </em>he said. <em>“I passed all my fall semester classes and raised my GPA to a 3.2.”</em>

Patients with convergence insufficiency commonly complain of headaches and blurred, or double vision while doing close work, such as on the computer or at their desk. They frequently have short attention spans and problems remembering what they’ve read. They often squint or rub their eyes.

<em>“Many times these problems are diagnosed as learning disorders,” </em>Dr. Davis said, <em>“when in actuality, a vision problem is the culprit. That’s why we’re here.”</em>

Dr. Davis administers a comprehensive vision exam which includes visual skills testing to determine how the eyes work at close distances and as a coordinated team. The tests also measure muscle control and other age-appropriate visual perceptions.

But better grades aren’t the only benefit Kevin has seen from vision therapy. <em>“I’ve grown more confident socially and my sense of humor has improved,” </em>he said with a smile. <em>“I feel like I accomplish things quicker. My lifetime goal of becoming a police officer is now obtainable – and I’m sure I’ll be a good one.”</em>

<em>“I’d recommend Dr. Davis’ vision therapy to anyone. It changed my life and it can change yours.”</em>

Dr. Tod Davis Developmental Optometry and Vision Therapy Services offices are located in Gainesville, Fredericksburg and Winchester, Virginia.

###]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Twenty year-old Kevin was beginning to think his dream of becoming a police officer would never happen. He had trouble concentrating on his schoolwork and, even though he studied constantly...]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>177</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-01-26 18:40:45</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-01-26 18:40:45</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>vision-therapy-puts-patient-on-track-to-realize-career-goals</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>3D Technology: Now Screening Eyes Everywhere</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=183</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2012 13:56:40 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=183</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<em>by Dr. Tod R. Davis</em>

Recently, the new 3D technology has been receiving a significant amount of attention, especially with the option of 3D at the theaters, a new Nintendo 3DS, classroom use of 3D technology, and even 3D home televisions. The American Optometric Association, with the explosion of 3D technology, has issued a public health warning article titled “3D in the Classroom: See Well, Learn Well.” The purpose of the article is to educate the public about people who are uncomfortable with watching 3D, as there have been an increasing number of these reports.

What does it mean to be uncomfortable with viewing 3D on a screen? In most cases, this is a strong sign of a binocular vision disorder, such as convergence insufficiency. <!--more-->Convergence insufficiency is when the eyes have issues working together at close range, also known as an eye teaming problem, where the eyes drift out despite trying to do near work. In an effort to keep the eyes working, the individual has to: make an extra effort to bring the eyes together (which causes fatigue, headache, etc.); cover one eye; or, the brain will actually suppress the vision in one eye, all to avoid swimming letters and double vision.

Some people have said that if watching 3D movies bothers an individual, than that individual should simply not look at 3D screens. However, the reality is that an issue with viewing 3D properly is strong evidence that there’s a problem with the viewer’s binocular vision.

There has always been 3D for people: The real world and binocular vision work together to create the same effect. In fact, 3D viewing technologies enable us to screen for vision disorders in a new and very efficient way: When someone with a vision disorder watches a program or movie, or plays a game which utilizes this technology, they suffer from the “3D’s of Viewing 3D: dizziness, discomfort and lack of depth.” This is also known as 3D Vision Syndrome, and it reveals vision disorders such as convergence insufficiency.

Here is the good news: binocular conditions such as convergence insufficiency are treatable. This is where vision therapy comes in. Vision therapy can help a child (or an adult, even) with eye teaming issues. People that struggle to do work at close range – or that struggle to watch 3D screens – don’t have to continue to struggle, and through the work of vision therapy they can retrain the eyes to work together properly, giving them both excellent binocular vision in real life, and the ability to watch 3D screens.

In addition, viewing anything in 3D, be it a video game, movie, or television program, has no worse impact on the viewer than the 2D equivalent. Certainly, you should limit the viewing of television, especially for children; yet, this is true whether the television is in 2D or 3D. This makes 3D technology a boon to schools, homes, and theaters as more and more people are “tested” for vision disorders (such as convergence insufficiency) in the name of education and fun!

I maintain that for these reasons, the increase in 3D technology is a good thing. The use of the 3D technology has been, and will continue to be, extremely helpful in the diagnosis of vision disorders such as convergence insufficiency.

<strong>Sources &amp; Resources:</strong>
“3D in the Classroom: See Well, Learn Well” editorial by Dominick M. Maino, OD, Med, FAAO, FCOVD-A

<a href="http://covdblog.wordpress.com/2010/06/04/3-d-vision-syndrome%E2%80%A6linked-to-%E2%80%9Cadd-like%E2%80%9D-behaviors-in-children/" target="_blank">"3-D Vision Syndrome...linked to 'ADD-like' behaviors in children"</a> by D. Fortenbacher, O.D., FCOVD

<a href="http://www.aoa.org/x20026.xml" target="_blank">The American Optometric Associations's page on 3D</a>

<a href="http://viewer.zmags.com/publication/d0eb8af9#/d0eb8af9/1" target="_blank">"3D in the Classroom: See Well, Learn Well"</a> by the American Optometric Association

<a href="http://www.3deyehealth.org/" target="_blank">A site dedicated to 3D Vision &amp; Eye Health</a> by the American Optometric Association

<a href="http://www.convergenceinsufficiency.org/#whatis" target="_blank">"What is Convergence Insufficiency?"</a> by the Optometrists Network]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Some people have said that if watching 3D movies bothers an individual, than that individual should simply not look at 3D screens. However, the reality is that an issue with viewing 3D properly is strong evidence that there’s a problem with the viewer’s binocular vision.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>183</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-01-31 13:56:40</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-01-31 13:56:40</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>3d-technology-now-screening-eyes-everywhere</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Success Story of Annie</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=192</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2012 20:30:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=192</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA["My daughter, Annie*, has ADHD, and she has been treated for it for many years with prescription medications. The medicine didn’t fully treat the problem, though it did help. However, we noticed drastic changes in her behavior once she started vision therapy.
<!--more-->
Numerous people at our church commented on how much Annie had “grown up” and “matured” over the summer. I never told any of them that she was in vision therapy, and was surprised to hear such. I had to laugh to myself because the only thing that we had changed over the summer was starting vision therapy for Annie.

We used to struggle to get our daughter to do homework. It was like a tug of war whenever she came home from school. Usually, all we could do is get her to rush through her homework right before she went to bed.

Within six sessions after Annie started with the therapy, I noticed that she was coming home less frustrated. Part of this was her having been prescribed with bifocals by Dr. Davis. Even more amazing was that when I asked about her homework, she said that she had completed the work at school during their free time. Huh? Is this the same kid?

Annie’s homework assignments used to look rushed and sloppy. After starting to see Dr. Davis, her handwriting has become much neater, and she is able to pay a lot more attention to her work.

Vision therapy has been one of the single most beneficial things we have done for our daughter. It has grounded her, calmed her, and allowed her world to open up.

Thank you Dr. Davis, for making such a wonderful difference in my daughter’s life!"

<em><strong>*Privacy Statement:</strong>
The above is an actual story from one of our clients. Minimal edits have been made for readability, and names have been changed to protect the privacy of the client. Dr. Davis cares deeply about the privacy of all of his clients, and all information in the above success story was volunteered by the client.</em>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[My daughter has ADHD, and she has been treated for it for many years with prescription medications. The medicine didn’t fully treat the problem, though it did help. However, we noticed drastic changes in her behavior once she started vision therapy.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>192</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-02-06 20:30:25</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-02-06 20:30:25</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>success-story-of-annie</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Follow Up on Gracie V.</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=203</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2012 16:46:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=203</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[We're excited to report that Gracie V. is approximately halfway through her vision therapy treatment, and she continues to show a great deal of progress! <a href="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/success-story-of-gracie-v/" target="_blank">(To read her previous testimony, click here.)</a> In a follow-up appointment after eight months of therapy, Gracie's vision has improved in the following areas:<!--more-->
<ul>
	<li>Oculomotor Function (eye tracking)</li>
	<li>Binocularity (locating objects)</li>
	<li>Focus (identifying objects)</li>
	<li>Reflexes</li>
	<li>Vestibular Integration</li>
	<li>Form Memory</li>
	<li>Sequential Memory</li><br />
</ul>
Additionally, Gracie's parents have reported, in a self-evaluation, improvement in the following areas:
<ul>
	<li>Reading Ability</li>
	<li>Reading Comprehension</li>
	<li>Reading Endurance</li>
	<li>Reading Independence</li>
	<li>Loss of Place Frequency While Reading</li>
	<li>Oral Reading Fluidity</li>
	<li>Reading Enjoyment</li>
	<li>Reading Fatigue</li>
	<li>Handwriting</li>
	<li>Spelling</li>
	<li>Educational Enjoyment</li>
	<li>Ease of Study</li>
	<li>Self-Confidence</li>
	<li>Self-Esteem</li>
	<li>Concentration</li>
	<li>Attention Span</li>
	<li>Happiness</li>
	<li>Memory</li>
	<li>Sports</li>
	<li>Clumsiness</li>
	<li>Ocular Control</li>
	<li>Distance Vision</li>
	<li>Depth Perception</li>
	<li>Peripheral Vision</li><br />
</ul>
Gracie's father gives the following statement in light of the progress we have made through our vision therapy sessions with Gracie:

"We recently started section 3 of vision therapy and Grace still very much enjoys it. The therapy is fun to her, rather than work. The home exercises prescribed for section 3 are also very enjoyable, even as we get more and more involved with actual eye functions. When we first walked through the door in Dr. Davis' office, we never could have imagined that she would have made the progress she has made already. It’s been truly remarkable! We can hardly wait for more improvements, and we're sure they are on their way. Whatever the cause was of Gracie’s vision problems, we know for a fact: Vision Therapy <em>is</em> the answer."]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA["We recently started section 3 of vision therapy and Grace still very much enjoys it. The therapy is fun to her, rather than work."]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>203</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-02-24 16:46:48</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-02-24 16:46:48</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>follow-up-on-gracie-v</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Success Story of Jack B.</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=223</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2012 15:57:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=223</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Jack B., a child who has previously been diagnosed with Asperger’s Syndrome, was brought to our office by his mother Amy P. on suspicion that some of Jack’s learning difficulties were vision-related. At the end of the therapy, Amy P. and Jack are excited by the results.
<!--more-->
"Improvement everywhere!" says Amy P. "Jack had many issues prior to starting vision therapy, at school as well as at home. After vision therapy, Jack is more focused, more relaxed, and far happier than before treatment. Homework is now very easy for Jack, and getting him to do his chores and other tasks around the house are no longer a struggle. His reading comprehension has gone way up, and he enjoys reading far more now. In fact, Jack is now one of the strongest readers in his class, and has been placed in an advanced reader’s program! 

"Jack received straight A’s on his report card for the first time in his life, and has enjoyed vision therapy immensely. He has repeatedly talked about how much he will miss the therapy sessions. 'Ms. Beth' has been an absolute joy to work with, and she made therapy both fun and challenging. Thank you so much, Dr. Davis!"

]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Jack B., a child who has previously been diagnosed with Asperger’s Syndrome, was brought to our office by his mother Amy P. on suspicion that some of Jack’s learning difficulties were vision-related. At the end of the therapy, Amy P. and Jack are excited by the results.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>223</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-02-28 15:57:44</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-02-28 15:57:44</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>success-story-of-jack-b</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Success Story of Emily</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=228</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 May 2012 17:49:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=228</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[We love hearing about the impact that our work is having on the lives of the children and families we treat. It’s our personal goal to change lives and to improve children’s ability to learn through treatment of vision disorders. Esther and Ben have graciously provided us with this great testimony for their thirteen-year-old child, Emily:
<!--more-->

<blockquote>Emily was always a good student and liked school. However, she had been having headaches, stomachaches, and would sometimes complain about having trouble seeing things.  Our optometrist referred us to Dr. Tod Davis for vision therapy. We found out that she had been seeing double when reading, and struggled with tasks at school like copying from the board, and multiple-choice tests which required “filling in the bubbles” to give an answer. We later realized that she was compensating, getting notes from friends at school rather than copying from the board in order to maintain her grades.

I’m a family therapist and was interested in the research, so I was all for it. My husband, however, was a little skeptical about having Emily undergo the therapy. During the one year process, he asked at one point, "How do we know that this is really helping?" However, by the end of it, there was definitely a difference in Emily’s vision and we both were so glad that we had made the commitment to vision therapy.

After vision therapy, Emily is much more confident at school, especially in math where copying numbers had been a real challenge. Now that the convergence issue has been resolved, she is able to read much faster.  She is now truly enjoying school and reading more. She occasionally uses her glasses at times when there is a lot of reading or computer work involved, but she rarely needs them anymore. Vision therapy has made a huge difference!</blockquote>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[We love hearing about the impact that our work is having on the lives of the children and families we treat. It’s our personal goal to change lives and to improve children’s ability to learn through treatment of vision disorders. Esther and Ben have graciously provided us with this great testimony for their thirteen-year-old child, Emily:]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>228</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-05-16 17:49:01</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-05-16 17:49:01</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>success-story-of-emily</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Gifted Children and Vision Disorders</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=235</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Jun 2012 18:16:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=235</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[It might come as a surprise, but there are gifted children that have vision disorders. A child may not necessarily be exhibiting signs of a learning issue (such as fussing over homework or showing a slower progression among their classmates) in order for a vision disorder to be present. Even children who are otherwise gifted learners can still suffer from vision disorders. Therefore, convergence insufficiency, amblyopia, and other disorders of vision are not and should not be attributed only to “slow learners” or “reluctant readers.”
<!--more-->
Difficulty learning is usually the sign of a vision problem that most parents pay attention to. Because of this, it is often the case that an intelligent child is not brought in for diagnosis until their academic performance suffers. At this point, the parents are often confused by the child’s struggles in certain areas. The parents may even mistake the reduced performance, such as on a written test, as a sign of laziness in the child. These children are often performing adequately enough to not qualify for additional in-school help, which can reinforce this assumption.

Another thing to note is that the gifted child may otherwise be extremely verbal, and do perfectly on verbal tests. In fact, he or she may be able to answer questions on a written test correctly when asked them verbally. When there is a disparity such as this, seeking a thorough vision screening should be a parent’s immediate reaction. A functional vision test goes far beyond the “20/20” eye chart examination with which we are all so familiar. This vision assessment tests the full range visual health factors, including eye tracking, eye teaming and convergence. By testing all aspects of vision, this screening uncovers vision disorders such as convergence insufficiency, amblyopia, eye-teaming issues and computer vision syndrome.

When such disorders come to light, the good news is that they are often treatable without surgery or glasses. Vision therapy, a series of exercises meant to re-train the eyes to function according to their intended function, corrects a wide variety of vision disorders. The result is that the child is better able to see and interpret written materials, allowing their natural giftedness to shine through all the more.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[It might come as a surprise, but there are gifted children that have vision disorders. A child may not necessarily be exhibiting signs of a learning issue (such as fussing over homework or showing a slower progression among their classmates) in order for a vision disorder to be present. Even children who are otherwise gifted learners can still suffer from vision disorders. Therefore, convergence insufficiency, amblyopia, and other disorders of vision are not and should not be attributed only to “slow learners” or “reluctant readers.”]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>235</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-06-15 18:16:38</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-06-15 18:16:38</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>gifted-children-and-vision-disorders</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>How Convergence Insufficiency Can Sometimes Act Like ADHD</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=239</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Jun 2012 14:00:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=239</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[If your child has trouble focusing on reading, writing, or a homework assignment for more than 15 minutes at a time, you have probably been told that his or her symptoms suggest Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) as the underlying cause. However, with symptoms that often are similar to each other, vision disorders in children may sometimes be misdiagnosed as ADHD.
<!--more-->
Convergence insufficiency is a common visual disorder which affects the coordination of the eyes. An estimated 1 in 20 children suffer from convergence insufficiency. But, what is convergence insufficiency? First, let me explain the concept of convergence: When reading, writing, drawing, or doing other work that requires up-close attention, a person’s eyes must turn in, or converge, in order for the image of the work to be clear. 

Convergence happens smoothly and subconsciously in those without convergence insufficiency. However, those who suffer from the disorder have difficulty turning their eyes inward. As a result, conscious effort must be made to focus on close objects, which is very tiring. 

Have you ever crossed your eyes? Imagine feeling like you had to do that in order to read, and imagine being expected to maintain that focus for minutes or even hours at a time. This is how reading feels to those with convergence insufficiency. It’s no wonder they have difficulty focusing on their work! 

This extra exertion, naturally, causes a number of uncomfortable symptoms, such as eyestrain, headaches and blurred vision. Children with convergence insufficiency may experience difficulty concentrating, read slowly, read the same line repeatedly, have trouble remembering what they read, or frequently lose their place. This may result in inattentiveness at school and while completing homework, or a general avoidance of such close work.

Here’s the problem: To a parent, or even a medical practitioner, all of these symptoms suggest ADHD. Those with convergence insufficiency may even have 20/20 vision, further complicating diagnoses. In a 2000 study, it was demonstrated that children diagnosed with ADHD are three times more likely to have convergence insufficiency than children who have not been so diagnosed. Clearly, there is reason to believe that some of those children would not need ADHD medications if their struggle with convergence insufficiency was to be fully addressed and treated. 

This is why we recommend the following: If your child has been diagnosed with ADHD, or is exhibiting some of the signs of convergence insufficiency or ADHD, a thorough developmental vision exam by a developmental optometrist should be your first step in treating the disorder. It’s a decision that could save your child the stigma of being diagnosed with ADHD, and save you money on medications.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[If your child has trouble focusing on reading, writing, or a homework assignment for more than 15 minutes at a time, you have probably been told that his or her symptoms suggest Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) as the underlying cause. However, with symptoms that often are similar to each other, vision disorders in children may sometimes be misdiagnosed as ADHD.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>239</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-06-21 14:00:09</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-06-21 14:00:09</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>how-convergence-insufficiency-can-sometimes-act-like-adhd</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Is Your Child Ready for Fall Sports?</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=309</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2012 08:30:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=309</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[School has started back up, which means a lot of children and families are already thinking about fall sports. Especially in varsity sports, many of the teams have already had their tryouts, and have probably been conditioning all summer in preparation for the intense competitions ahead. This is exciting for many students, but there are also many who will avoid sports entirely. Why is this? Obvious differences in personality aside, many students feel as though they are too clumsy to “make the cut.” There are many potential causes for this, but did you know that vision disorders are among them? Two vision disorders which affect visual tracking, an important skill in many sports, are amblyopia and strabismus.

Strabismus occurs when the two eyes do not physically fixate on the same point, resulting in one eye appearing to be “turned” out, in, up or down. The two disorders can occur simultaneously, with strabismus being the cause of amblyopia (known as strabismic amblyopia). However, the presence of strabismus does not imply the presence of amblyopia, and vice versa. Sometimes, even if a child suffers from strabismus, it may be that the eye turn is so small that it is not noticeable by a visual examination.

While strabismus describes a physical “eye turn,” amblyopia describes the condition where the brain suppresses or ignores information coming from one eye, resulting in uneven visual acuity and, in extreme cases, blindness in one eye. Either disorder can negatively impact stereoscopy, or the ability to see in three dimensions. Without stereoscopy, depth perception and hand-eye coordination suffer in a sports setting.

Issues in visual acuity are often the first vision problems to be noticed by parents, as “20/20” acuity screenings are often part of a sport physical and are occasionally required by the school for all students. However, when there still seems to be a visual problem in the child, even after testing yields a “20/20” result or the proper lenses are prescribed, a vision disorder should be your next suspect. A vision disorder, left untreated, can affect a student’s academics as well as their sports performance. If you believe you or your child may have a vision disorder, help is available. Don’t wait. A behavioral eye examination can determine the nature and cause of the disorder and allow for a corrective procedure plan to be developed. Call Dr. Tod R. Davis Developmental Optometry & Vision Therapy Services today to get started.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[School has started back up, which means a lot of children and families are already thinking about fall sports. Especially in varsity sports, many of the teams have already had their tryouts, and have probably been conditioning all summer in preparation for the intense competitions ahead. This is exciting for many students, but there are also many who will avoid sports entirely. Why is this? Obvious differences in personality aside, many students feel as though they are too clumsy to “make the cut.” There are many potential causes for this, but did you know that vision disorders are among them? Two vision disorders which affect visual tracking, an important skill in many sports, are amblyopia and strabismus.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>309</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-09-28 08:30:49</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-09-28 08:30:49</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>is-your-child-ready-for-fall-sports</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>future</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>College and Beyond: A Success Story from Kelsey Conway</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=245</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2012 18:42:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=245</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Kelsey’s story has a single message of hope, which can serve as great comfort for all parents who have children that suffer from eye problems.  Kelsey Conway came to Dr. Davis when she was 16 years old with “major eye problems” and the help she received from vision therapy has allowed her to become successful in life.  According to Cindy Conway, Kelsey’s mother, five years after vision therapy she has recently graduated from Mary Washington with a B. A. in Historic Preservation and a minor in Museum Studies.  Not only did Kelsey graduate in four years, but she achieved Summa Cum Laude!  She was able to achieve this goal with no special help or accommodations.  She hopes to pursue a master’s degree, but is currently looking for a job in her field.  Kelsey’s inspiring testimony below was written after she had received a year’s worth of vision therapy at age 17:
<!--more-->
<blockquote>I don’t think that I will ever forget when Dr. Davis looked at me and stated frankly, “You have major eye problems.”  I cried right then and there.  It was an answer, yes, to a question that had been hanging over me since second grade.  Unfortunately, it was in no way, shape, or form the answer I had wanted.  It didn’t matter that over half the population of the United States have these problems.  What is half a country at a time when one feels entirely alone?  I was scared, furious, and truly devastated.

From the time I was small, I had odd little quirks.  When I wasn’t knocking into things or falling down for no apparent reason, (I did this so often my parents nicknamed me Lump Head and gave me a theme song), I was making silly errors in school, which resembled Dyslexia.  My most serious defect was in spelling.  Even after years of rules and phonics, I would spell the same word three different ways in one paper.  Reading was second in line on my list of grievances.  I read slowly, stumbling often and misreading entire sentences.  Math, though least defined, was just as exasperating.  The number of errors my work contained was just as embarrassing as it was frustrating.  Because these difficulties persisted, when I was 16 years old my parents called in the help of a tutor.  The tutor realized that I did not need her expertise, so I was sent to Fredericksburg Learning Center for testing.  These tests revealed that I did not have Dyslexia, but that the answer to my problems lay in an area of vision we had never heard of before, Developmental Optometry.  It was then that Dr. Davis diagnosed me with Binocular Fusion Disorder, using these three terrible words, “major eye problems.”

Binocular Fusion Disorder can be described as visual overload.  My eyes do not work together to send my brain correct, easily processed information.  This causes my brain to simply shut off certain functions of my eyes.  Periphery is one thing my brain annihilated, giving me tunnel vision.  It also represses whichever of my eyes is acting up, and generally wreaks havoc on my ability to connect the sensory dots.  I do not know if my brain does this out of desperation or revenge, but I am now working to train my eyes to get along and have my brain stay out of their business.  Weekly therapy sessions with Dr. and Mrs. Davis and the support from my wonderful family, have helped me through this whole mess.

I had a lot of issues getting over the initial shock and denial, which accompanied my diagnosis. Then came a blatant loathe and resistance to the many therapy exercises including ‘Stick Near Far’, ‘The Star Chart’, and ‘The Duck and Pigeon’.  Dr. and Mrs. Davis gave me these exercises and many other nifty contraptions, instructing me to flail about until I felt completely and utterly ridiculous, all to retrain my misbehaving eyes.  One thing I continue to hold in contempt is my prism glasses.  I am supposed to wear them for all close-up work because my eyes, even today, get fatigued and I end up two inches from the paper.  Even so, eye therapy has helped more than I expected.  The initial “And how on earth is this going to help?” has passed, and things are going much smoother.

Though my math still contains many careless mistakes (I am beginning to suspect I am just a poor mathematician and it has nothing to do with my eyes), my spelling has begun to improve.  Reading is easier, and I am proud to announce that I have shed the nickname Lump Head!  It has taken over a year, and I am not completely finished ridding my eyes of their nasty little habits.  At times I wonder if I will ever be able to spell ‘another’ without adding an uninvited ‘u’, or if I will ever be able to read like Speedy Gonzales, but I know I will never let this be an excuse to give up.  Perhaps I may encounter obstacles between myself and my dreams, but “major eye problems” are no longer among them.</blockquote>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Kelsey’s story has a single message of hope, which can serve as great comfort for all parents who have children that suffer from eye problems.  Kelsey Conway came to Dr. Davis when she was 16 years old with “major eye problems” and the help she received from vision therapy has allowed her to become successful in life.  Kelsey’s inspiring testimony below was written after she had received a year’s worth of vision therapy at age 17:]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>245</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-07-10 18:42:49</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-07-10 18:42:49</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>college-and-beyond-a-success-story-from-kelsey-conway</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Can Long Bangs Cause Lazy Eye?</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=255</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2012 12:00:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=255</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[One Australian ophthalmologist believes that haircuts with long bangs, like the style popularized by Justin Bieber, could cause lazy eye due to the eye’s vision being obstructed. 

<a href=http://www.wibc.com/news/Story.aspx?ID=1705179>Here’s a link in case you don’t believe us.</a>

Personally, we are not convinced, and believe that the doctor will have to answer and supply proof for several questions before the theory would hold any weight. Here are some of those questions:
<!--more-->
<strong>Does Hair Obstruct Vision Totally?</strong>

For the claim that hair in your eyes causes vision problems to hold much water, it would have to be demonstrable that the presence of hair over one’s eye obscures vision from that eye just as much as would wearing an eye patch. We suppose that this is theoretically possible, but would require a particularly thick volume of hair over that eye. Such a thick lock would probably not be kept over the eye, however, as it would rob the person of their ability to see depth effectively. If the wearer of such a hairstyle were involved in any sports, they would quickly see the need for keeping this amount of hair out of their eyes. This leads directly into our next question:

<strong>What is the Minimum Duration of Obstruction before Losing Vision?</strong>

Since we can surmise that an athlete would always keep their theoretically single-eye-blinding hair out of their eyes during a sporting event, we’ll pretend this is a non-athlete. We know that patching is used as part of lazy eye treatments, and is particularly effective against refractive amblyopia. However, even the best-case treatment requires patching for at least 2 – 8 hours per day for 3 months or longer, and this period of patching should be consecutive for best results. 

We also know that the vision in the non-lazy eye tends to recover quickly after patching. Thus, for hair obstruction of vision to work the <em>other</em> way and cause vision <em>loss</em> would require more consecutive obstruction for a longer period of time. Let’s pretend that this would happen at 10 hours per day over the course of one year. Now we have to ask just one more question.

<strong>What is the Likelihood of a “Hair Flip” Occurring During those 10 Hours?
</strong>
Think about it. Better yet, look at the picture on the link above. Justin Bieber’s hair is out of his eyes for that picture. How frequently does one specifically move their hair out of their eyes, either for pictures or because their hair is annoying them in its present position? It is highly unlikely that someone would willingly leave their hair in their eyes for 10 hours at one time. In fact, it would take a rather conscious effort by them to not move their hair (or do any activity which might move their hair) for their hair to, in fact, stay put for 10 hours on end.

Remember, this is assuming that the hair caused a perfect obstruction akin to an eye patch. Anything which did not cause this obstruction would most certainly not cause the vision of an eye to become blurry (though it certainly might obstruct vision). Perhaps the Australian ophthalmologist will someday develop some research which demonstrates by what mechanism thick bangs can cause vision loss, but with what we currently know about the eye, vision and vision disorders, this hardly seems plausible.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[One Australian ophthalmologist believes that haircuts with long bangs, like the style popularized by Justin Bieber, could cause lazy eye due to the eye’s vision being obstructed. For the claim that hair in your eyes causes vision problems to hold much water, it would have to be demonstrable that the presence of hair over one’s eye obscures vision from that eye just as much as would wearing an eye patch.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>255</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-07-16 12:00:44</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-07-16 12:00:44</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>can-long-bangs-cause-lazy-eye</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Dr. Davis Responds to Article on University of Cincinnati Baseball Players</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=262</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 19 Jul 2012 08:00:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=262</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<em>Dr. Tod R. Davis responds to "High-Performance Vision Training Improves Batting Statistics for University of Cincinnati Baseball Players"</em>

A common response from parents after vision therapy is that their child’s sports ability increases. “Thomas has played in baseball since he was six,” says Nancy M., Thomas’ grandmother. “However, it wasn’t until after vision therapy that Thomas, who had convergence insufficiency and eye-tracking issues, went from often missing the ball by three inches to hitting, catching, and pitching with amazing accuracy!” Not only do academic abilities improve with vision therapy, but on-the-field improvements occur as well.  Vision therapy allows for better tracking, better depth perception, better balance, better hand-eye coordination, and even better response time because the visual system has been trained to register faster.
<!--more-->
We’ve had numerous referrals from families with stories that go like this: George goes through a year of vision therapy, and the next year joins the same sports team he was in last year, say baseball, with his friend Johnny.  Johnny’s parents are so impressed with George’s improved performance compared to the previous year that they ask George’s parents what sports camp they put George through.  George’s parents simply reply, “We didn’t.  George had vision therapy.”  So, Johnny’s parents investigate vision therapy, and decide they want vision therapy for Johnny too – not because he’s showing obvious signs of a vision disorder, but because they have seen the results of what training the eyes to work with the brain-to-hand motion can do for a child.

On a national level, over the last several years, there has been more attention given to the benefits of vision therapy for athletes. There was an article in the Washington Times on June 13th titled “Eyes Have It With Help of Special Spectacles,” in which several players on the Washington National’s team are using the Nike Strobe glasses, another method of vision therapy.  (We actually will be providing these through the office for those that are interested.)  This has been the norm with most sports teams, where a few select players on a team receive vision therapy.

This particular article titled “High Performance Vision Training Improves Batting Statistics for University of Cincinnati Baseball Players” that I am responding to, however, is unusual in that the whole-team participated.  The team’s batting average – the team, not a single player – “increased from 0.251 in 2010 to 0.285 in 2011 and the slugging percentage increased by 0.033.  The rest of the Big East’s slugging percentage fell over that same time frame 0.082.”  For those not familiar with baseball, this is huge, especially for an entire team’s batting average.

I suspect that vision therapy – eye vision training – is going to become more integrated into sports and sports training for both children, as well as adults in the upcoming years, and I think this article speaks towards that.

<em><a href="http://www.plosone.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0029109 " target="_blank">“High-Performance Vision Training Improves Batting Statistics for University of Cincinnati Baseball Players”</a> by Joseph F. Clark, James K. Ellis, Johnny Bench (Hall of Fame catcher from Cincinnati Reds), Jane Khoury, and Pat Graman.</em>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[A common response from parents after vision therapy is that their child’s sports ability increases. “Thomas has played in baseball since he was six,” says Nancy M., Thomas’ grandmother. “However, it wasn’t until after vision therapy that Thomas, who had convergence insufficiency and eye-tracking issues, went from often missing the ball by three inches to hitting, catching, and pitching with amazing accuracy!” Not only do academic abilities improve with vision therapy, but on-the-field improvements occur as well.  Vision therapy allows for better tracking, better depth perception, better balance, better hand-eye coordination, and even better response time because the visual system has been trained to register faster.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>262</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-07-19 08:00:10</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-07-19 08:00:10</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>dr-davis-responds-to-article-on-university-of-cincinnati-baseball-players</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Vision Therapy, Cost, and Health Insurance</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=268</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2012 13:18:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=268</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Maybe you’re past the point of asking “What is vision therapy?” and your child (or yourself) has gone through the tests by the developmental optometrist and has shown areas needing vision therapy, and you’re ready to try this.  Then the dreaded “cost” issue comes up.
<!--more-->
The first question that probably comes to your mind is, “Does my health insurance cover this?”  Unfortunately, many health insurance companies refuse to cover vision therapy, especially if the therapy appears to be “non-medical” in what it’s addressing.  This can be especially frustrating if your health insurance covers other kinds of therapy.

On top of this, truly effective vision therapy requires a one-on-one therapist with at-home exercises, which can increase the cost versus a computerized vision therapy regimen or completely at-home exercises, which research has shown to be no more effective than a placebo.

So what are you to do?  Your child obviously shows signs of vision disorders, and more than likely your son or daughter’s enjoyment of life, school, learning, and even sports has been negatively affected by their struggles with their vision.  Yet the sheer cost of vision therapy is enough to make people balk.

Oftentimes, we like to point out to those that are this stage, that vision therapy can be related to braces.  Health insurance doesn’t cover all of the cost of braces for most people.  And yet people simply put priority on getting their child braces and make it happen financially.  Although for some people braces are to address a painful or upcoming issue, many people get braces for purely cosmetic reasons.

Keeping in mind that vision therapy affects multiple facets of your ability to read, retain, and process information, and even in day-to-day life in areas of balance and the ability to measure depth and distance in our three-dimensional world, how much more important is vision therapy compared to a cosmetic reason?  We’re not here to say you should pick vision therapy over braces – please, by no means think that – but sometimes we find that people’s priorities for their child’s or even their own are skewed to think that vision therapy is not that important.

We not just trying to sell you on this, either; we perform our jobs eagerly to see our patients’ eyes light up as they realize they no longer see everything doubled up, or words stop blurring, or they can pitch, catch, and bat a baseball, or they stop bumping into corners, or they’re able to sit down and learn when before it was too tiring and caused a headache. The increased confidence, the relief as their struggle to learn is removed, and the smiles are why we do what we do.

Now, this doesn’t remove the obstacle of cost, especially if your health insurance won’t help.  We here at Developmental Optometry &amp; Vision Therapy Services know you have a family to feed, a mortgage to pay, cars to maintain, and lives to live.  So we’ve developed some ways to help you deal with the cost so that you can more easily enjoy the life-changing benefits of vision therapy, such as offering financial plans with up to 18 months of no-interest.

If you’ve been debating the cost of vision therapy, or if you suspect that you or your child may have vision problems, please call us at the number at the top, or click on the Contact Us button, and we’ll work with you to address your vision needs.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Maybe you’re past the point of asking “What is vision therapy?” and your child (or yourself) has gone through the tests by the developmental optometrist and has shown areas needing vision therapy, and you’re ready to try this.  Then the dreaded “cost” issue comes up.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>268</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-08-15 13:18:43</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-08-15 13:18:43</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>vision-therapy-cost-and-health-insurance</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Convergence Insufficiency Sufferers Still Ignored by Many Eye Doctors</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=274</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Aug 2012 12:30:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=274</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[This article at the <a href="http://visionhelp.wordpress.com/2012/05/22/convergence-insufficiency-a-diagnosis-that-begins-with-bright-spots/" target="_blank">VisionHelp Blog</a> pointed out a unique problem which is facing eye doctors today. The problem is this: Despite randomized controlled trials, or RCTs, which demonstrate the effectiveness of vision therapy for the treatment of convergence insufficiency, many eye doctors still fail to test for the disorder. Some even going so far as to dismiss the efficacy of vision therapy. The Convergence Insufficiency Treatment Trial (or CITT) conclusively demonstrates that convergence insufficiency is best treated by a combination of in-office vision therapy exercises and at-home reinforcement exercises.
<!--more-->
As a result of eye doctors throughout the country failing to support what <a href="http://convergenceinsufficiency.net/uploads/CITT_Arch_2008.pdf" target="_blank">the current science suggests</a>, convergence insufficiency remains a relatively unknown disorder. However, just because it’s unknown doesn’t mean it’s uncommon. <strong>1 in 12</strong> people suffer from this disorder, and all of the symptoms associated with it:
<ul>
	<li>Headaches with reading or during close work</li>
	<li>Loss of attention and concentration for reading or during close work</li>
	<li>Words moving or doubling when reading or during close work</li>
	<li>Eye fatigue and/or discomfort with reading or during close work</li>
	<li>Homework battles: 20 minutes of homework takes hours</li>
</ul>
It’s unfortunate that these individuals are far more likely to be diagnosed with ADHD or ADD rather than convergence insufficiency. With Ritalin and Adderall shortages occurring more and more frequently, you would think that this issue would be gaining more attention, if for no other reason than as a possible underlying cause of the spike in ADHD and ADD diagnoses. No such luck.

In a study done by Dr. Davis B. Granet with 266 patients with CI (convergence insufficiency), there is “an apparent three-fold greater incidence of ADHD among patients with CI when compared with the incidence of ADHD in the general US population (1.8-3.3%) (Leslie et al., 2004). We also note a seeming three-fold greater incidence of CI in the ADHD population. This may simply represent an association and not be a causative relationship. Until further studies are performed, however, patients diagnosed with ADHD should be evaluated to identify the small subset that may have CI – a condition that responds well to treatment at home.”

We work hard to raise awareness about the vision disorders which are so often ignored, and to treat those who are suffering from such disorders. Our goal is to always be one of the “Bright Spots” which the VisionHelp Blog describes. If your child has been diagnosed with ADHD or ADD, but has not had a thorough vision screening by a developmental eye doctor, you may be treating the symptoms when it is possible to treat the cause: Vision therapy has been proven to treat convergence insufficiency, and may be able to help your child focus without the use of medications.

<em>See “The Relationship Between Convergence Insufficiency and ADHD” by Dr. David B. Granet.</em>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Despite randomized controlled trials, or RCTs, which demonstrate the effectiveness of vision therapy for the treatment of convergence insufficiency, many eye doctors still fail to test for the disorder, even going so far as to dismiss the efficacy of vision therapy. The Convergence Insufficiency Treatment Trial (or CITT) conclusively demonstrates that convergence insufficiency is best treated by a combination of in-office vision therapy exercises and at-home reinforcement exercises.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>274</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-08-29 12:30:04</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-08-29 12:30:04</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>convergence-insufficiency-sufferers-still-ignored-by-many-eye-doctors</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>August is National Vision &amp; Learning Month</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=289</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Aug 2012 14:49:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=289</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<strong><em>Is your child ready to go back to school?</em></strong>

Just two or three months ago children couldn’t wait to get out of school.  The freedom of summer was just around the bend, and they eagerly looked forward to the break.  However, once they’ve had their fill of summer, these same children begin to anticipate school: They are entering a new grade, perhaps a new school.  For some children, buying school supplies and perhaps even new school outfits can be exciting and escalate their desire to return to learn new studies.

Yet there are some children who dread going back to school.  <!--more-->There are a wide variety of reasons for this, and for some of those kids it’s their struggle with academics.  Namely, the struggle with homework, or seeing the board clearly, or reading correctly out loud in class, makes many tummies upset.  Perhaps it’s the headaches that make children begin to dread going to class, their eyes getting tired halfway through the day.  For some children it’s even their sports abilities – who really enjoys looking like a fool on the field?

August is National Vision & Learning Month, and as part of that, we here at Developmental Optometry & Vision Therapy Services want to put out a reminder that having 20/20 eyesight does not mean that there are no vision issues.  In fact, it has been proven that children can have “perfect eyesight” and yet continue to experience vision disorders that make their school life miserable.

Vision disorders include things like the better-known lazy eye, but it also includes problems like convergence insufficiency and amblyopia, to name a few.  Many learning-related vision disorders can manifest themselves in children as symptoms that may not initially appear to be vision-caused. In fact, in some kids it can appear as ADD or ADHD symptoms, including: failure to give close attention to details, failure to listen when spoken to directly, frequently misplacing items, forgetfulness in daily activities, easily distracted, and difficulty remaining seated.

In a study done by Dr. Davis B. Granet with 266 patients with CI (convergence insufficiency), there is “an apparent three-fold greater incidence of ADHD among patients with CI when compared with the incidence of ADHD in the general US population (1.8-3.3%) (Leslie et al., 2004). We also note a seeming three-fold greater incidence of CI in the ADHD population. This may simply represent an association and not be a causative relationship. Until further studies are performed, however, patients diagnosed with ADHD should be evaluated to identify the small subset that may have CI – a condition that responds well to treatment at home.”

In honor of National Vision & Learning Month, please take a few moments to observe your child, and if you suspect there may be vision problems outside of 20/20 eyesight, take your child to a certified developmental optometrist.  Learning should be an exciting time for kids, and school a place to study and grow in skills, not something to dread.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[August is National Vision & Learning Month, and as part of that, we here at Developmental Optometry & Vision Therapy Services want to put out a reminder that having 20/20 eyesight does not mean that there are no vision issues.  In fact, it has been proven that children can have “perfect eyesight” and yet continue to experience vision disorders that make their school life miserable.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>289</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-08-16 14:49:47</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-08-16 14:49:47</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>august-is-national-vision-learning-month</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Success Story of &quot;Christina&quot;</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=303</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2012 13:35:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=303</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[We work hard in order to provide the best vision therapy treatments in the area, and love nothing more than to see how our hard work yields major life change in the children and adults with whom we work. We are here to create these moments, and we are always happy when a family is willing to share their successes:<!--more-->

<em>Christina’s 4th grade teacher first recommended that she have an assessment when she noticed Christina was having trouble reading. Christina would start out reading one sentence and finish on another sentence. We were referred to a reputable pediatric optometrist who confirmed that Christina had convergence insufficiency. The optometrist recommended that we order a CD to work on twice each week, and that this should solve her problem. However, since Christina had had this problem for quite some time, I felt that I needed a second opinion. I spoke to a nurse at St. Timothy’s whose son was in vision therapy. That’s when I heard about Dr. Davis.  

To be perfectly honest, Dr. Davis could have told me anything. My concern was my daughter’s eyes.  With her history, no other options available, I took a leap of faith with Dr. Davis, and we are very happy with the results.  

Vision therapy required several nights of homework and commitment: Christina argued about doing all the work but we made a point of doing it exactly as Dr. Davis had prescribed. After talking with another parent, I felt that the homework, along with the in-office visits, were the key to Christina’s success.  

When Christina finished her end of therapy evaluation, she said she knew she was done because she had “rocked” all of the testing. She could see and tell the difference from her initial evaluation. Vision therapy has increased Christina’s self-confidence and self-esteem and made her reading and comprehension stronger.</em>   

<strong>Privacy Statement:</strong>
The above is an actual story from one of our clients. Minimal edits have been made for readability, and names have been changed to protect the privacy of the client. Dr. Davis cares deeply about the privacy of all of his clients, and all information in the above success story was volunteered by the client.
]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[We work hard in order to provide the best vision therapy treatments in the area, and love nothing more than to see how our hard work yields major life change in the children and adults with whom we work. We are here to create these moments, and we are always happy when a family is willing to share their successes:]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>303</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-09-25 13:35:01</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-09-25 13:35:01</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>success-story-of-christina</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>It is a long established fact that a reader will be distracted</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=333</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2013 22:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/?p=333</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[There are many variations of passages of Lorem Ipsum available, but the majority have suffered alteration in some form, by injected humour, or randomised words which don't look even slightly believable. If you are going to use a passage of Lorem Ipsum, you need to be sure there isn't anything embarrassing hidden in the middle of text. All the Lorem Ipsum generators on the Internet tend to repeat predefined chunks as necessary, making this the first true generator on the Internet. It uses a dictionary of over 200 Latin words, combined with a handful of model sentence structures, to generate Lorem Ipsum which looks reasonable. The generated Lorem Ipsum is therefore always free from repetition, injected humour, or non-characteristic words etc.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>333</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-01-15 22:02:00</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-01-15 22:02:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>testing</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Lorem Ipsum is simply dummy text.</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=337</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2013 22:08:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/?p=337</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Contrary to popular belief, Lorem Ipsum is not simply random text. It has roots in a piece of classical Latin literature from 45 BC, making it over 2000 years old. Richard McClintock, a Latin professor at Hampden-Sydney College in Virginia, looked up one of the more obscure Latin words, consectetur, from a Lorem Ipsum passage, and going through the cites of the word in classical literature, discovered the undoubtable source. Lorem Ipsum comes from sections 1.10.32 and 1.10.33 of "de Finibus Bonorum et Malorum" (The Extremes of Good and Evil) by Cicero, written in 45 BC. This book is a treatise on the theory of ethics, very popular during the Renaissance. The first line of Lorem Ipsum, "Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet..", comes from a line in section 1.10.32]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>337</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-01-15 22:08:52</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-01-15 22:08:52</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>testing-two</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Accommodative Amplitude: So Close, Yet So Far</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=391</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 20:20:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/?p=391</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Eyes are amazing structures, moving about, translating visual pictures into cognitive information that tells us an awful lot about our world. Seeing things up close requires something called accommodation. The amount of change that occurs in the lens of an eye, as it moves from relaxed to what is termed fully accommodated, is called the amplitude of accommodation. Contraction of the ciliary muscle causes the lens to move away from the sclera, becoming rounder and changing the diopter power of the eye. The measurement of accommodation in each eye is taken separately.

For adults, the measurement at which things in the near visual field can be seen clearly is about 20 inches. For a child, that field is reduced to just 2-3 inches. For a young adult the field is about at 4-6 inches, and for an 80-year-old? 60 inches. The greatest change in accommodation amplitude seems to occur between the third and fifth decade of life.

As we age, our lenses lose elasticity, and thus, we are unable to focus on near field objects as clearly as we when we were young. Tasks such as threading a needle or reading label ingredients on personal care products or food cartons become next to impossible without magnifying glasses.

To test for near field accommodation, schedule an appointment with Dr. Tod Davis Developmental Optometry & Vision Therapy Services. Dr. Davis has been treating patients and helping them work through vision disorders with vision therapy programs for over 25 years in Easter Virginia. ]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>391</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-01-30 20:20:37</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-01-30 20:20:37</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>accommodative-amplitude-so-close-yet-so-far</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Is Your Vision Equal?</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=393</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 20:23:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/?p=393</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Nature sees to it that most babies come into the world in nearly perfect form. For 14 percent, however, the world is a little lopsided. They are among babies born with anisometropia. That means there is a large disparity between the two eyes in visual acuity. It also usually means the child will develop amblyopia, or lazy eye, in the first five years of life. One and one-half percent of the babies born each year come into the world with both anisometropia and amblyopia. The more severe the difference in vision between the eyes, the more likely it is that amblyopia, if not already present, will surface.

Some anisometropics are nearsighted in one eye and farsighted in the other, creating an entirely different set of challenges, but in most cases both eyes are either far or nearsighted, with the vision in one eye being quite good, and the other being quite poor. Depth perception, hand-eye coordination, and other vision problems can result from this inequality of vision.

With such a large refractive error, it is likely that vision will be impacted by accommodation, the process by which the brain receives visual communication from the stronger eye while ignoring the blurry images from the weaker eye. The longer the process continues, the weaker the eye with poor vision gets, until, in some cases, there is complete vision loss in that eye.

Treatment is usually centered on corrective lenses. The earlier the condition is diagnosed and treated, the easier it is to correct. Scheduling an appointment for a comprehensive eye exam with Dr. Tod Davis Developmental Optometry & Vision Therapy Services can help to determine the best treatment for your individual condition. Treating patients in the Eastern Virginia area for over 25 years, Dr. Davis is skilled at developing a program of vision therapy that will have you seeing the world at its best in no time.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>393</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-01-30 20:23:20</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-01-30 20:23:20</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>is-your-vision-equal</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title> Dancing Eyes and the Nystagmus Test</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=395</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 20:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/?p=395</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Nystagmus is the involuntary dancing and darting of the eyes, even when focused in a steady gaze, as they quickly move from side to side, or up and down. Some are born with the condition. Others acquire it through diseases like MS, brain tumors, diabetes, or head injuries. Others may experience the condition as a side effect from prescription medicine. Some experience nystagmus caused by nicotine, bright light flashes, hyperventilation, or deep vibration.

There are two types of nystagmus. Optokinetic nystagmus is caused within the eye, whereas vestibular nystagmus stems from the inner ear. Inner ear problems may cause jerk nystagmus, where the eyes move slowly in one direction, then jerk back across the visual field, which can cause vertigo as well as nausea. The condition improves with age, but worsens as one tires.

There is one other cause for nystagmus, however: inebriation. If an individual is drunk, their eyes will dance if they attempt to fix their gaze to the extreme left or right. This was discovered by a vision therapist, and the discovery has led to the development of the horizontal gaze nystagmus test, frequently used in field sobriety tests by police officers today.

There are surgical procedures that seem to help with hereditary nystagmus. Additional treatments include botox, although with temporary results, and biofeedback therapy. Corrective lenses can improve vision for those with nystagmus.

Surgery, drugs, and even acupuncture have been shown to be effective treatments for nystagmus, in addition to recent pharmaceutical discoveries that help smooth the eye movements. If you have questions regarding nystagmus, or any other vision disorders, and need intelligent, up-to-date answers, contact Dr. Tod Davis Developmental Optometry & Vision Therapy Services. Dr. Davis has been providing reliable vision therapy evaluation and care for patients in Northern Virginia for over 25 years. ]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>395</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-01-30 20:24:00</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-01-30 20:24:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>dancing-eyes-and-the-nystagmus-test</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Convergence Insufficiency Sufferers Still Ignored by Many Eye Doctors </title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=398</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 20:24:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/?p=398</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[This article at the VisionHelp Blog pointed out a unique problem which is facing eye doctors today. The problem is this: Despite randomized controlled trials, or RCTs, which demonstrate the effectiveness of vision therapy for the treatment of convergence insufficiency, many eye doctors still fail to test for the disorder. Some even going so far as to dismiss the efficacy of vision therapy. The Convergence Insufficiency Treatment Trial (or CITT) conclusively demonstrates that convergence insufficiency is best treated by a combination of in-office vision therapy exercises and at-home reinforcement exercises.

As a result of eye doctors throughout the country failing to support what the current science suggests, convergence insufficiency remains a relatively unknown disorder. However, just because it’s unknown doesn’t mean it’s uncommon. 1 in 12 people suffer from this disorder, and all of the symptoms associated with it:

    Headaches with reading or during close work
    Loss of attention and concentration for reading or during close work
    Words moving or doubling when reading or during close work
    Eye fatigue and/or discomfort with reading or during close work
    Homework battles: 20 minutes of homework takes hours

It’s unfortunate that these individuals are far more likely to be diagnosed with ADHD or ADD rather than convergence insufficiency. With Ritalin and Adderall shortages occurring more and more frequently, you would think that this issue would be gaining more attention, if for no other reason than as a possible underlying cause of the spike in ADHD and ADD diagnoses. No such luck.

In a study done by Dr. Davis B. Granet with 266 patients with CI (convergence insufficiency), there is “an apparent three-fold greater incidence of ADHD among patients with CI when compared with the incidence of ADHD in the general US population (1.8-3.3%) (Leslie et al., 2004). We also note a seeming three-fold greater incidence of CI in the ADHD population. This may simply represent an association and not be a causative relationship. Until further studies are performed, however, patients diagnosed with ADHD should be evaluated to identify the small subset that may have CI – a condition that responds well to treatment at home.”

We work hard to raise awareness about the vision disorders which are so often ignored, and to treat those who are suffering from such disorders. Our goal is to always be one of the “Bright Spots” which the VisionHelp Blog describes. If your child has been diagnosed with ADHD or ADD, but has not had a thorough vision screening by a developmental eye doctor, you may be treating the symptoms when it is possible to treat the cause: Vision therapy has been proven to treat convergence insufficiency, and may be able to help your child focus without the use of medications.

See “The Relationship Between Convergence Insufficiency and ADHD” by Dr. David B. Granet.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>398</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-01-30 20:24:43</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-01-30 20:24:43</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>convergence-insufficiency-sufferers-still-ignored-by-many-eye-doctors-2</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title> August is National Vision &amp; Learning Month</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=400</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 20:33:46 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/?p=400</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Is your child ready to go back to school?

Just two or three months ago children couldn’t wait to get out of school. The freedom of summer was just around the bend, and they eagerly looked forward to the break. However, once they’ve had their fill of summer, these same children begin to anticipate school: They are entering a new grade, perhaps a new school. For some children, buying school supplies and perhaps even new school outfits can be exciting and escalate their desire to return to learn new studies.

Yet there are some children who dread going back to school. There are a wide variety of reasons for this, and for some of those kids it’s their struggle with academics. Namely, the struggle with homework, or seeing the board clearly, or reading correctly out loud in class, makes many tummies upset. Perhaps it’s the headaches that make children begin to dread going to class, their eyes getting tired halfway through the day. For some children it’s even their sports abilities – who really enjoys looking like a fool on the field?

August is National Vision & Learning Month, and as part of that, we here at Developmental Optometry & Vision Therapy Services want to put out a reminder that having 20/20 eyesight does not mean that there are no vision issues. In fact, it has been proven that children can have “perfect eyesight” and yet continue to experience vision disorders that make their school life miserable.

Vision disorders include things like the better-known lazy eye, but it also includes problems like convergence insufficiency and amblyopia, to name a few. Many learning-related vision disorders can manifest themselves in children as symptoms that may not initially appear to be vision-caused. In fact, in some kids it can appear as ADD or ADHD symptoms, including: failure to give close attention to details, failure to listen when spoken to directly, frequently misplacing items, forgetfulness in daily activities, easily distracted, and difficulty remaining seated.

In a study done by Dr. Davis B. Granet with 266 patients with CI (convergence insufficiency), there is “an apparent three-fold greater incidence of ADHD among patients with CI when compared with the incidence of ADHD in the general US population (1.8-3.3%) (Leslie et al., 2004). We also note a seeming three-fold greater incidence of CI in the ADHD population. This may simply represent an association and not be a causative relationship. Until further studies are performed, however, patients diagnosed with ADHD should be evaluated to identify the small subset that may have CI – a condition that responds well to treatment at home.”

In honor of National Vision & Learning Month, please take a few moments to observe your child, and if you suspect there may be vision problems outside of 20/20 eyesight, take your child to a certified developmental optometrist. Learning should be an exciting time for kids, and school a place to study and grow in skills, not something to dread.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>400</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-01-30 20:33:46</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-01-30 20:33:46</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>august-is-national-vision-learning-month-2</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title> Vision Therapy, Cost, and Health Insurance</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=402</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 20:34:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/?p=402</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Maybe you’re past the point of asking “What is vision therapy?” and your child (or yourself) has gone through the tests by the developmental optometrist and has shown areas needing vision therapy, and you’re ready to try this. Then the dreaded “cost” issue comes up.

The first question that probably comes to your mind is, “Does my health insurance cover this?” Unfortunately, many health insurance companies refuse to cover vision therapy, especially if the therapy appears to be “non-medical” in what it’s addressing. This can be especially frustrating if your health insurance covers other kinds of therapy.

On top of this, truly effective vision therapy requires a one-on-one therapist with at-home exercises, which can increase the cost versus a computerized vision therapy regimen or completely at-home exercises, which research has shown to be no more effective than a placebo.

So what are you to do? Your child obviously shows signs of vision disorders, and more than likely your son or daughter’s enjoyment of life, school, learning, and even sports has been negatively affected by their struggles with their vision. Yet the sheer cost of vision therapy is enough to make people balk.

Oftentimes, we like to point out to those that are this stage, that vision therapy can be related to braces. Health insurance doesn’t cover all of the cost of braces for most people. And yet people simply put priority on getting their child braces and make it happen financially. Although for some people braces are to address a painful or upcoming issue, many people get braces for purely cosmetic reasons.

Keeping in mind that vision therapy affects multiple facets of your ability to read, retain, and process information, and even in day-to-day life in areas of balance and the ability to measure depth and distance in our three-dimensional world, how much more important is vision therapy compared to a cosmetic reason? We’re not here to say you should pick vision therapy over braces – please, by no means think that – but sometimes we find that people’s priorities for their child’s or even their own are skewed to think that vision therapy is not that important.

We not just trying to sell you on this, either; we perform our jobs eagerly to see our patients’ eyes light up as they realize they no longer see everything doubled up, or words stop blurring, or they can pitch, catch, and bat a baseball, or they stop bumping into corners, or they’re able to sit down and learn when before it was too tiring and caused a headache. The increased confidence, the relief as their struggle to learn is removed, and the smiles are why we do what we do.

Now, this doesn’t remove the obstacle of cost, especially if your health insurance won’t help. We here at Developmental Optometry & Vision Therapy Services know you have a family to feed, a mortgage to pay, cars to maintain, and lives to live. So we’ve developed some ways to help you deal with the cost so that you can more easily enjoy the life-changing benefits of vision therapy, such as offering financial plans with up to 18 months of no-interest.

If you’ve been debating the cost of vision therapy, or if you suspect that you or your child may have vision problems, please call us at the number at the top, or click on the Contact Us button, and we’ll work with you to address your vision needs.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>402</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-01-30 20:34:16</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-01-30 20:34:16</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>vision-therapy-cost-and-health-insurance-2</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Dr. Davis Responds to Article on University of Cincinnati Baseball Players</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=404</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 20:36:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/?p=404</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Dr. Tod R. Davis responds to “High-Performance Vision Training Improves Batting Statistics for University of Cincinnati Baseball Players”

A common response from parents after vision therapy is that their child’s sports ability increases. “Thomas has played in baseball since he was six,” says Nancy M., Thomas’ grandmother. “However, it wasn’t until after vision therapy that Thomas, who had convergence insufficiency and eye-tracking issues, went from often missing the ball by three inches to hitting, catching, and pitching with amazing accuracy!” Not only do academic abilities improve with vision therapy, but on-the-field improvements occur as well. Vision therapy allows for better tracking, better depth perception, better balance, better hand-eye coordination, and even better response time because the visual system has been trained to register faster.

We’ve had numerous referrals from families with stories that go like this: George goes through a year of vision therapy, and the next year joins the same sports team he was in last year, say baseball, with his friend Johnny. Johnny’s parents are so impressed with George’s improved performance compared to the previous year that they ask George’s parents what sports camp they put George through. George’s parents simply reply, “We didn’t. George had vision therapy.” So, Johnny’s parents investigate vision therapy, and decide they want vision therapy for Johnny too – not because he’s showing obvious signs of a vision disorder, but because they have seen the results of what training the eyes to work with the brain-to-hand motion can do for a child.

On a national level, over the last several years, there has been more attention given to the benefits of vision therapy for athletes. There was an article in the Washington Times on June 13th titled “Eyes Have It With Help of Special Spectacles,” in which several players on the Washington National’s team are using the Nike Strobe glasses, another method of vision therapy. (We actually will be providing these through the office for those that are interested.) This has been the norm with most sports teams, where a few select players on a team receive vision therapy.

This particular article titled “High Performance Vision Training Improves Batting Statistics for University of Cincinnati Baseball Players” that I am responding to, however, is unusual in that the whole-team participated. The team’s batting average – the team, not a single player – “increased from 0.251 in 2010 to 0.285 in 2011 and the slugging percentage increased by 0.033. The rest of the Big East’s slugging percentage fell over that same time frame 0.082.” For those not familiar with baseball, this is huge, especially for an entire team’s batting average.

I suspect that vision therapy – eye vision training – is going to become more integrated into sports and sports training for both children, as well as adults in the upcoming years, and I think this article speaks towards that.

“<a href="http://www.plosone.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0029109 " target="_blank">High-Performance Vision Training Improves Batting Statistics for University of Cincinnati Baseball Players</a>” by Joseph F. Clark, James K. Ellis, Johnny Bench (Hall of Fame catcher from Cincinnati Reds), Jane Khoury, and Pat Graman.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>404</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-01-30 20:36:06</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-01-30 20:36:06</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>dr-davis-responds-to-article-on-university-of-cincinnati-baseball-players-2</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Can Long Bangs Cause Lazy Eye? </title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=406</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 20:36:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/?p=406</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[One Australian ophthalmologist believes that haircuts with long bangs, like the style popularized by Justin Bieber, could cause lazy eye due to the eye’s vision being obstructed.

<strong>Here’s a link in case you don’t believe us.</strong>

Personally, we are not convinced, and believe that the doctor will have to answer and supply proof for several questions before the theory would hold any weight. Here are some of those questions:

<strong>Does Hair Obstruct Vision Totally?</strong>

For the claim that hair in your eyes causes vision problems to hold much water, it would have to be demonstrable that the presence of hair over one’s eye obscures vision from that eye just as much as would wearing an eye patch. We suppose that this is theoretically possible, but would require a particularly thick volume of hair over that eye. Such a thick lock would probably not be kept over the eye, however, as it would rob the person of their ability to see depth effectively. If the wearer of such a hairstyle were involved in any sports, they would quickly see the need for keeping this amount of hair out of their eyes. This leads directly into our next question:

<strong>What is the Minimum Duration of Obstruction before Losing Vision?</strong>

Since we can surmise that an athlete would always keep their theoretically single-eye-blinding hair out of their eyes during a sporting event, we’ll pretend this is a non-athlete. We know that patching is used as part of lazy eye treatments, and is particularly effective against refractive amblyopia. However, even the best-case treatment requires patching for at least 2 – 8 hours per day for 3 months or longer, and this period of patching should be consecutive for best results.

We also know that the vision in the non-lazy eye tends to recover quickly after patching. Thus, for hair obstruction of vision to work the other way and cause vision loss would require more consecutive obstruction for a longer period of time. Let’s pretend that this would happen at 10 hours per day over the course of one year. Now we have to ask just one more question.
<strong>
What is the Likelihood of a “Hair Flip” Occurring During those 10 Hours?</strong>

Think about it. Better yet, look at the picture on the link above. Justin Bieber’s hair is out of his eyes for that picture. How frequently does one specifically move their hair out of their eyes, either for pictures or because their hair is annoying them in its present position? It is highly unlikely that someone would willingly leave their hair in their eyes for 10 hours at one time. In fact, it would take a rather conscious effort by them to not move their hair (or do any activity which might move their hair) for their hair to, in fact, stay put for 10 hours on end.

Remember, this is assuming that the hair caused a perfect obstruction akin to an eye patch. Anything which did not cause this obstruction would most certainly not cause the vision of an eye to become blurry (though it certainly might obstruct vision). Perhaps the Australian ophthalmologist will someday develop some research which demonstrates by what mechanism thick bangs can cause vision loss, but with what we currently know about the eye, vision and vision disorders, this hardly seems plausible.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>406</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-01-30 20:36:45</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-01-30 20:36:45</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>can-long-bangs-cause-lazy-eye-2</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>How Convergence Insufficiency Can Sometimes Act Like ADHD</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=409</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 20:38:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/?p=409</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[If your child has trouble focusing on reading, writing, or a homework assignment for more than 15 minutes at a time, you have probably been told that his or her symptoms suggest Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) as the underlying cause. However, with symptoms that often are similar to each other, vision disorders in children may sometimes be misdiagnosed as ADHD.

Convergence insufficiency is a common visual disorder which affects the coordination of the eyes. An estimated 1 in 20 children suffer from convergence insufficiency. But, what is convergence insufficiency? First, let me explain the concept of convergence: When reading, writing, drawing, or doing other work that requires up-close attention, a person’s eyes must turn in, or converge, in order for the image of the work to be clear.

Convergence happens smoothly and subconsciously in those without convergence insufficiency. However, those who suffer from the disorder have difficulty turning their eyes inward. As a result, conscious effort must be made to focus on close objects, which is very tiring.

Have you ever crossed your eyes? Imagine feeling like you had to do that in order to read, and imagine being expected to maintain that focus for minutes or even hours at a time. This is how reading feels to those with convergence insufficiency. It’s no wonder they have difficulty focusing on their work!

This extra exertion, naturally, causes a number of uncomfortable symptoms, such as eyestrain, headaches and blurred vision. Children with convergence insufficiency may experience difficulty concentrating, read slowly, read the same line repeatedly, have trouble remembering what they read, or frequently lose their place. This may result in inattentiveness at school and while completing homework, or a general avoidance of such close work.

Here’s the problem: To a parent, or even a medical practitioner, all of these symptoms suggest ADHD. Those with convergence insufficiency may even have 20/20 vision, further complicating diagnoses. In a 2000 study, it was demonstrated that children diagnosed with ADHD are three times more likely to have convergence insufficiency than children who have not been so diagnosed. Clearly, there is reason to believe that some of those children would not need ADHD medications if their struggle with convergence insufficiency was to be fully addressed and treated.

This is why we recommend the following: If your child has been diagnosed with ADHD, or is exhibiting some of the signs of convergence insufficiency or ADHD, a thorough developmental vision exam by a developmental optometrist should be your first step in treating the disorder. It’s a decision that could save your child the stigma of being diagnosed with ADHD, and save you money on medications.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>409</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-01-30 20:38:06</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-01-30 20:38:06</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>how-convergence-insufficiency-can-sometimes-act-like-adhd-2</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Gifted Children and Vision Disorders </title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=412</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 20:38:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/?p=412</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/16.jpg"><img src="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/16-150x150.jpg" alt="" title="1" width="150" height="150" class="alignnone size-thumbnail wp-image-433" /></a>It might come as a surprise, but there are gifted children that have vision disorders. A child may not necessarily be exhibiting signs of a learning issue (such as fussing over homework or showing a slower progression among their classmates) in order for a vision disorder to be present. Even children who are otherwise gifted learners can still suffer from vision disorders. Therefore, convergence insufficiency, amblyopia, and other disorders of vision are not and should not be attributed only to “slow learners” or “reluctant readers.”

Difficulty learning is usually the sign of a vision problem that most parents pay attention to. Because of this, it is often the case that an intelligent child is not brought in for diagnosis until their academic performance suffers. At this point, the parents are often confused by the child’s struggles in certain areas. The parents may even mistake the reduced performance, such as on a written test, as a sign of laziness in the child. These children are often performing adequately enough to not qualify for additional in-school help, which can reinforce this assumption.

Another thing to note is that the gifted child may otherwise be extremely verbal, and do perfectly on verbal tests. In fact, he or she may be able to answer questions on a written test correctly when asked them verbally. When there is a disparity such as this, seeking a thorough vision screening should be a parent’s immediate reaction. A functional vision test goes far beyond the “20/20” eye chart examination with which we are all so familiar. This vision assessment tests the full range visual health factors, including eye tracking, eye teaming and convergence. By testing all aspects of vision, this screening uncovers vision disorders such as convergence insufficiency, amblyopia, eye-teaming issues and computer vision syndrome.

When such disorders come to light, the good news is that they are often treatable without surgery or glasses. Vision therapy, a series of exercises meant to re-train the eyes to function according to their intended function, corrects a wide variety of vision disorders. The result is that the child is better able to see and interpret written materials, allowing their natural giftedness to shine through all the more.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>412</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-01-30 20:38:55</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-01-30 20:38:55</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>gifted-children-and-vision-disorders-2</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Vision Therapy: Helping ASD Patients Approach Normal</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=449</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2013 15:20:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=449</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Autism Spectrum Disorder, or ASD, has risen significantly along with speculation about causes and development of treatment programs over the past few decades. The wide range of levels of function embraced by those with the disorder, along with the uncertainty about causes, has combined to create some confusion about what ASD really is. The result is that by December of 2013, there will be a reconfigured, more definitive description of the symptoms that determine an ASD diagnosis.<!--more-->

Many ASD patients suffer from vision disorders related to processing and interpretation of visual images in addition to more common disorders regarding acuity, tracking, eye teaming, focusing, near or farsightedness, and astigmatism. Additionally, there is between a 20 and 50 percent greater chance of strabismus in ASD patients than in normal individuals. 

Such disorders contribute to the collection of unusual behaviors found in ASD patients, including toe walking, side viewing, limited visual attention, difficulty coordinating central and peripheral vision, and other actions related to speech and perceptive abilities. Children that seem normal at birth sometimes begin to develop symptoms related to ASD, passing early milestones without problems but experiencing increasingly slower progress as they approach more complicated tasks. 

Developmental ophthalmologists and developmental optometrists can test and diagnose many correctable vision problems that might go undetected in a regular eye exam. Improvements are usually noted between two to twelve months after beginning treatment, and can have a lifetime impact, keeping patients engaged in mainstream educational and social environments. 

Early detection combined with a vision therapy program designed by an experienced professional, such as Dr. Tod Davis, can minimize delays in learning and cognition, improving vision performance through corrective lenses, prisms, physical exercises and computer games designed to strengthen weaker visual function. Dr. Tod Davis Developmental Optometry and Vision Therapy Services can put over 30 years of experience to work for patients experiencing an ASD diagnosis, creating a vision therapy program specifically designed to deliver optimum performance from each and every patient.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Many ASD patients suffer from vision disorders related to processing and interpretation of visual images in addition to more common disorders regarding acuity, tracking, eye teaming, focusing, near- or far-sightedness, and astigmatism. Additionally, there is between a 20 and 50 percent greater chance of strabismus in ASD patients than in normal individuals.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>449</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-03-04 15:20:55</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-03-04 15:20:55</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>vision-therapy-helping-asd-patients-approach-normal</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Lazy Eye: Surgery or Therapy? </title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=451</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2013 09:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=451</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Lazy eye, or amblyopia, comes in two flavors: refractive and strabismic. When there is great disparity in acuity between refractive errors of the eyes, the stronger eye often takes over, effectively erasing the visual information sent from the weaker eye. Eventually, refractive amblyopia finds one eye doing most or all of the work, while the other eye does nothing. <!--more-->

In strabismic amblyopia, one or both eyes are turned, creating two separate sets of visual information resulting in double vision. The brain turns off the information from one eye to avoid seeing double, leaving the other eye without a task. It is possible, over time, to completely lose sight in the weaker or lazy eye.

Treatment of amblyopia usually involves disabling the stronger eye in some way, either patching, drops, or a contact lens, forcing the weaker eye to gradually strengthen and learn to function. Sometimes, a program of disabling is coupled with surgery to physically correct a turned eye. While that presents a cosmetic solution to the problem, the weaker eye still has not been trained to work, and will likely continue to remain weak even though aesthetically normal. 

It was once thought that only children under the age of six could be treated for amblyopia, however, many adults that grew up without the benefit of treatment have undergone a successful program of visual therapy, experiencing highly successful results from combinations of glasses, patching or disabling, and vision therapy. Stories of people well into their 50s and 60s finally achieving binocular vision through vision therapy programs are well documented. 

Experienced developmental ophthalmologists and developmental optometrists, like Dr. Tod Davis, can work with a variety of patients experiencing a broad range of amblyopic conditions, applying over 35 years of experience to the task for successful treatment. Amblyopic patients throughout the Eastern Virginia region should schedule an exam with the staff at Dr. Tod Davis Developmental Optometry and Vision Therapy Services to experience peak performance through a combined program of state of the art treatments.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Treatment of amblyopia usually involves disabling the stronger eye in some way, either patching, drops, or a contact lens, forcing the weaker eye to gradually strengthen and learn to function. Sometimes, a program of disabling is coupled with surgery to physically correct a turned eye. While that presents a cosmetic solution to the problem, the weaker eye still has not been trained to work, and will likely continue to remain weak even though aesthetically normal. ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>451</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-03-11 09:30:00</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-03-11 09:30:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>lazy-eye-surgery-or-therapy</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Vision Therapy: Who Benefits?</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=453</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2013 09:30:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=453</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Vision therapy can be as individual as a fingerprint, with programs designed to address very specific sets of vision disorders displayed by an individual patient.  Results of such individualized programs in large, significant studies, administered to a broad range of functional levels in patients with varying degrees of success, is both expensive and difficult to obtain, and therefore quite rare. Success stories, however, relating positive experiences from patients that have seen dramatic improvements, are plentiful. So, then, who does benefit from vision therapy?<!--more-->

The truth is, everyone. Vision therapy offers exercises for both home and office visits, for common vision disorders like crossed or lazy eyes, tracking or movement problems, depth perception and eye teaming, as well as near and far sightedness, and astigmatism. In addition, vision therapy can help with eyes stressed by spending long hours each day staring at computer screens. It can help active sports figures hone skills to shave seconds off of reaction times, sharpen hand to eye accuracy, and improve peripheral vision. 

Vision therapy can provide struggling students with strategies to improve reading and learning skills, turning dreaded tasks into fun challenges. It can deliver ways to accommodate visual processing disorders to improve performance. Just as many types of exercises and activities can improve physical performance, vision therapy programs can provide the means to crank up vision performance several notches. 

Dr. Tod Davis has been working with patients presenting a wide variety of vision disorders for over 35 years. His experience offers patients throughout the Northern Virginia region state of the art therapy programs and equipment designed to bring out the best possible visual performance for each patient. Scheduling a comprehensive exam with the staff at Dr. Tod Davis Developmental Ophthalmology and Vision Therapy Services could mean the difference between success and failure, in school, in sports, or in careers.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Vision therapy can provide struggling students with strategies to improve reading and learning skills, turning dreaded tasks into fun challenges. It can deliver ways to accommodate visual processing disorders to improve performance. Just as many types of exercises and activities can improve physical performance, vision therapy programs can provide the means to crank up vision performance several notches. ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>453</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-03-25 09:30:45</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-03-25 09:30:45</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>vision-therapy-who-benefits</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Early Signs of Reading Difficulties</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=465</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 16:49:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=465</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/Reading-Difficulty1.jpg"><img class="alignleft size-full wp-image-483" title="Reading Difficulty" src="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/Reading-Difficulty1.jpg" alt="" width="232" height="300" /></a>

<a href="http://www.readingrockets.org/article/33170/">There are a number of causes of reading difficulties in children and adults; learning disabilities like dyslexia or issues related to vision development. Many parents and teachers find this problem challenging and often feel ill equipped to address the issue. Early detection of reading difficulties is important. The following article outlines early signs which could lead to reading difficulties.
http://www.readingrockets.org</a>

Once you have identified that your child may be exhibiting early signs of reading difficulties, the next step is to seek help in determining the cause. Ask yourself if your child is demonstrating all or some of the following behaviors:

A book is held very close to the eyes
The head moves back and forth while reading
Finger is used to trace lines in the book
Murmuring or silent moving of lips (subvocalization)
Complaints of blurring, double-vision, or headaches
Short attention span while reading, fatigues quickly
Child seems to read well, but has poor recall
Child avoids long books in favor of short pieces to read

If you see these types of behaviors your child may be having vision problems. It may be time to seek the assistance of a Behavioral Optometrist who can diagnose specific vision problems and prescribe a highly specialized course of Vision Therapy to develop efficient vision skills and processing.  Dr’s Tod Davis OD, FCOVD and Amy Carlyle, OD, FAAO, Developmental Optometry and Vision Therapy Services have over 30 years of experience in diagnosing and treating vision related problems in the Northern Virginia area. Early detection and treatment can make a world of difference for you and your child.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>465</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-04-03 16:49:39</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-04-03 16:49:39</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>early-signs-of-reading-difficulties-2</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Famous Double Vision</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=492</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 19:21:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=492</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Double vision affects many people.  There are many causes of double vision, from developmental issues to brain injuries. No matter the cause, double vision can have mild to devastating effects on an individual.  Fortunately it can be treated in most cases through the use of specialized lenses, medical treatment and vision therapy.  The following blog addresses a recent and notable case of double vision, check it out.
<a href="http://visionhelp.wordpress.com/2013/01/26/hillary-clintons-double-vision/"><img src="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/Double-Vision3.jpg" alt="" title="Double Vision" width="577" height="609" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-499" /></a>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>492</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-04-03 19:21:11</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-04-03 19:21:11</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>famous-double-vision</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Wait! I Changed My Mind</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=518</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2013 21:22:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=518</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/Mind-Changing.jpg"><img src="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/Mind-Changing.jpg" alt="" title="Mind Changing" width="300" height="300" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-519" /></a><html /> It may seem that we only change our minds when making one decision for another, but in reality our minds are always changing, at least from a neurological point of view. Some of that change we have no direct control over like aging, disease and injury. With age, disease and injury we can reduce our susceptibility with reasonable measures, such as diet, exercise, and safety awareness. Then there is the change in our minds that we can directly control through challenging exercises that confront our minds with a certain level of difficulty and repetitive engagement.

	This relates to what is called brain plasticity (neuroplasticity), which is now widely accepted in the neurosciences and described in the book “Train Your Mind, Change Your Brain”, by Sharon Begley. Her book describes neuroplasticity as the ability of the brain to change in response to experience, revealing that the brain is capable of altering its structure and function. The brain can even generate new neurons, a power we retain well into old age. So, feel free to change your mind at any time!

	One aspect of “brain training” is Vision Therapy, a sequence of activities individually prescribed and monitored by a Developmental Optometrist. This type of therapy or brain training is designed to develop efficient visual skills and processing for individuals whose vision did not develop naturally, or who have experienced injury to the brain.  Many of these people experience a wide range of physical, academic and behavioral problems. In-office techniques utilize lenses, prisms, filters, and many other types of specialized equipment with corresponding home activities to reinforce developing visual skills.

	Vision Therapy changes the brain, specifically the visual system, by engaging the brain in repetitive, challenging tasks. In turn, these activities enhance existing neural pathways or create new ones.  The key to successful vision therapy is the right amount of difficulty.  In the book “The Talent Code,” author Daniel Coyle describes how the nervous system reinforces neurons and neural connections through repetition and maintaining a level of difficulty at the edge of failure, which he described as deep practice.

	Imagine a young girl rolling a soccer ball between her feet and trying to pop it up in the air in order to pass it to a team mate. She tries and fails repeatedly until she slows the process down and concentrates on simply rolling the ball onto her foot. In time she realizes the subtle movements needed to make the delicate pass. Now imagine our young soccer player repeating over and over the subtle maneuver with the ball until it becomes automatic and she is able to pass the ball to her teammate effortlessly. This is deep practice.<a href="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/Little-Girl-Soccer.jpg"><img src="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/Little-Girl-Soccer.jpg" alt="" title="Little Girl Soccer" width="300" height="267" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-535" /></a>

	The concept of deep practice is central to most vision therapy procedures. Tasks begin at the level of difficulty needed to induce minor failures which cause the patient to become increasingly aware of how they are performing, in other words self-evaluation. Vision therapy patients begin self-correction at the point of failure. They explore the edge of their abilities and begin to develop the required visual and motor skills necessary to move forward. This is repeated over and over again until there are no more levels of difficulty to achieve. This process causes the nervous system to reinforce the needed neural pathways. Once these pathways are reinforced their use becomes automated and permanent.

	Vision therapy is based on deep practice and the science of neuroplasticity. To learn more about vision therapy contact a developmental ophthalmologist or developmental optometrists, like Dr. Todd Davis and Dr. Amy Carlyle, Developmental Optometry - Vision Therapy – NeuroOptometry – Low Vision Services who can put over 30 years of experience to work for patients experiencing vision related issues. They can create a vision therapy program specifically designed to deliver optimum performance from each and every patient.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[It may seem that we only change our minds when making one decision for another, but in reality our minds are always changing, at least from a neurological point of view.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>518</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-04-25 21:22:41</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-04-25 21:22:41</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>wait-i-changed-my-mind</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Vision Therapy is Not Just for the Eyes: A Multi-Disciplinary Approach to Treating Dyslexia</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=539</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2013 18:57:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=539</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/Childs-eyes.jpg"><img src="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/Childs-eyes.jpg" alt="" title="Childs eyes" width="300" height="225" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-542" /></a>

Success today is heavily dependent on good vision. Digital displays are everywhere. Computers and cell phones, highway signs and academic classrooms. Not seeing or processing images well can impact one's opportunities adversely. 

It is of the utmost importance, when a child exhibits signs of difficulty in reading and cognitive skills, as with dyslexia, to have a thorough evaluation done. Perfect 20/20 vision does not tell the whole story. Nor does a regular physical exam. It is only when the visual and neurological matrix is embraced as an interconnected whole, and all functions relating to visual performance are examined, that an appropriate plan for treatment and management can be derived. 

The American Academy of Optometry and the American Optometric Association have developed a joint policy statement voicing the need for those at risk of cognitive or learning-related problems due to vision disorders to undergo a comprehensive vision exam including eye health along with eye function. A post-evaluation plan, including guidance for future treatment and referral to specialists, should make the assessment and recommendations known. 

The group notes that there are three parts of vision that are integral to the learning process: the visual pathway, visual efficiency, and information processing. The visual pathway includes all of the structures of the eye and brain that contribute to the learning process. Visual efficiency embraces movement, accommodation, teaming, and focusing. Information processing includes spatial awareness, coordination of vision with touch, sound, and the other senses, as well as identification and discrimination.

Like the visual process itself, dyslexia has a complex set of challenges that display acuity disorders in addition to processing and other physical errors. It is important to review all areas involved in cognitive tasks for academic work to truly assess a patient exhibiting dyslexic tendencies. 

Early detection and treatment or management of vision disorders related to dyslexia is advised, keeping the patient as functional and as on schedule as possible in relation to peers. That said, however, it is never too late to seek help for an adult with dyslexia, as many older patients find they are able to develop skills through the help of a developmental optometrist that they never thought would be possible. 

Vision therapy, sometimes thought to be connected with less effective treatment, is actually a proven, well-researched, and well-respected area of treatment for those suffering from vision disorders common to dyslexic individuals. Through use of exercises, lenses, and prisms patients are able to function as close to their goals as possible, enjoying academic pursuits and careers that would otherwise not be possible.

Dr. Tod Davis has treated patients with dyslexia for over 25 years, putting his expertise and experience to work creating programs that give patients the tools to succeed. Dr. Tod Davis Developmental Optometry and Vision Therapy Services can help in diagnosis and treatment of patients exhibiting difficulty with reading and other cognitive tasks, working to move patients toward goals that once seemed out of reach.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[It is of the utmost importance, when a child exhibits signs of difficulty in reading and cognitive skills, as with dyslexia, to have a thorough evaluation done. Perfect 20/20 vision does not tell the whole story. Nor does a regular physical exam. It is only when the visual and neurological matrix is embraced as an interconnected whole, and all functions relating to visual performance are examined, that an appropriate plan for treatment and management can be derived. ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>539</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-05-14 18:57:02</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-05-14 18:57:02</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>vision-therapy-is-not-just-for-the-eyes-a-multi-disciplinary-approach-to-treating-dyslexia</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Brain Injury Vision Disorders and Vision Therapy</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=549</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2013 18:55:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=549</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[href="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/Brain-Injury.jpg"><img src="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/Brain-Injury.jpg" alt="Brain Injury and Vision Therapy" title="Brain Injury" width="300" height="179" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-551" /></a>

Do you see with your eyes? Or do you see with your brain? 

The words on this page would be meaningless without interpretation by the brain. Likewise, beautiful images would be lost in translation without input from photoreceptive rods and cones in the retina. Vision, as we commonly refer to it, is a collaborative process engaging both eye and brain to fully enjoy a breathtaking sunset, or comprehend the writings of Shakespeare. 

When the brain suffers injury, either from trauma or stroke, the damage done to vision often takes three forms: visual field loss, diplopia (double vision), and/or visual balance disorders. 

Visual field loss often reduces a patient to central vision, making images and objects in the peripheral field invisible. Such limitations can prove dangerous for patients, as they navigate without the benefit of seeing moving vehicles, obstructions, or pitfalls outside of their present range. 

Diplopia often causes a patient to begin ignoring messages from the weaker eye in order to eliminate dizzying double images. Diplopia makes reading and close, intricate tasks, such as threading a needle or signing a document, both uncomfortable and frustrating. If left untreated, the weaker eye can eventually lose all capacity for sight.

Visual balance disorders, such as Midline Shift Disorder and/or visual neglect/imperceptions, can be especially troubling to brain injury patients.  Midline Shift Disorder moves the perception of an individual’s center line causing them to potentially lose their balance or misjudge their relation to an object.  Visual imperception disrupts the patient’s perception of where they are in space, putting them at risk of anything harmful in the neglected visual area.

<a href="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/thCAP40BH2.jpg"><img src="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/thCAP40BH2.jpg" alt="" title="Vision Therapy" width="369" height="314" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-554" /></a><a 

Vision therapy can improve many of the vision disorders associated with brain injuries. Developmental optometrists and developmental ophthalmologists can help patients by prescribing individualized vision therapy programs that improve a patient’s ability to determine their “place in space.” Behavioral and developmental optometrists understand how the eye and brain work together, and know how to test for specific vision disorders. Once tested, doctors like Dr. Tod Davis are able to design vision therapy programs that offer accommodative behaviors to decrease the likelihood of accidents caused by vision disorders, as well as design physical activities to strengthen skills. 

While every patient is different, experienced developmental optometrists have a library of therapeutic exercises and tools that can offer brain injured patients improved lifestyles through improved vision and perception skills. Dr. Tod Davis Developmental Optometry and Vision Therapy Services has been helping patients in a clinical setting for more than 25 years, developing exercises and lens combinations to help brain injured patients see the world in the best possible light. Scheduling an appointment to review vision disorders with Dr. Davis may offer solutions that less specialized exams overlook.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Do you see with your eyes? Or do you see with your brain? . . . When the brain suffers injury, either from trauma or stroke, the damage done to vision often takes three forms: visual field loss, diplopia (double vision), and/or visual balance disorders.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>549</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-05-22 18:55:06</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-05-22 18:55:06</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>brain-injury-vision-disorders-and-vision-therapy</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>I Can Read! A Vision Therapy Success Story</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=560</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2013 16:33:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=560</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Brady wanted us to share his success story with everyone. After thanking Dr. Davis and the therapist, Brady put it simply “I can read!” At Dr. Todd Davis and Dr. Amy Carlyle, Developmental Optometry - Vision Therapy and Low Vision services, we are always remarked by the power of vision therapy to change lives. Brady’s Mom noted “He came in with big challenges.” Once Brady dedicated himself to Vision Therapy he began to note obvious positive changes, like no longer seeing double.  Brady’s Mom saw other tangible benefits of his Vision Therapy, “This has also changed his self-esteem.” You can read their success stories below.
To learn more about vision therapy contact Dr. Todd Davis and Dr. Amy Carlyle, Developmental Optometry - Vision Therapy – NeuroOptometry – Low Vision Services, where we can put over 30 years of experience to work for patients experiencing vision related issues. Our Doctors and Vision Therapist can create a vision therapy program specifically designed to deliver optimum performance from each and every patient.

<a href="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/Brady-Success-Story1.jpg"><img src="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/Brady-Success-Story1.jpg" alt="" title="Brady Success Story" width="345" height="392" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-567" /></a>
<a href="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/Success-Story-Brady1.jpg"><img src="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/Success-Story-Brady1.jpg" alt="" title="Success Story Brady" width="342" height="396" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-568" /></a>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Brady wanted us to share his success story with everyone. After thanking Dr. Davis and the therapist, Brady put is simply “I can read!” At Dr. Todd Davis and Dr. Amy Carlyle, Developmental Optometry - Vision Therapy and Low Vision services, we are always remarked by the power of vision therapy to change lives.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>560</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-05-29 16:33:21</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-05-29 16:33:21</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>i-can-read-a-vision-therapy-success-story</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Two Eyes Are Better Than One! The Importance of Binocular Vision</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=573</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2013 21:25:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=573</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/Mike.jpg"><img src="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/Mike.jpg" alt="" title="Mike" width="480" height="360" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-575" /></a>

In the Pixar Movie Monsters Inc., Mike Wazowski is a lovable and laughable monster with one big eye (as seen above). Unfortunately for Mike, in the real world he would never enjoy the capability of binocular vision. Interestingly, having two eyes isn’t enough for binocular vision to occur.

Human eyes are designed to work as a team, both looking in the same direction at the same focal point, and returning similar images that the brain and visual system combine into one, stereoscopic, binocular view. 

Binocular vision is important in developing good depth perception, which in turn affects coordination and hand to eye skills. Without binocular vision, catching a baseball, making sense of classroom instructions on a blackboard or screen, and performing simple tasks such as walking or running becomes difficult. Those with impaired binocular vision often appear clumsy and uncoordinated because they lack the ability to orient themselves with relation to their environment.

One cause of poor binocular vision is eye alignment. The eyes, as described above, are not looking in the same direction. It is estimated that 3 percent of the population suffers from such issues. Another cause of poor binocular vision is a dramatic difference in acuity between the two eyes, with one eye seeing quite well and the other with a severe acuity issue. It is thought that as high as 12 percent of the population has binocular vision impairment.

Such vision disorders are sometimes missed in regular eye examinations. Should you suspect a binocular vision problem or another vision disorder, schedule and examination by a developmental optometrist, trained to diagnose and treat these conditions. Early treatment is the key and it ensures that children will not lag behind peers due to vision problems once they reach school age.

Ensure your child will progress to their full potential by scheduling a comprehensive exam with Dr. Tod Davis and Dr. Amy Carlyle Developmental Optometry and Vision Therapy Services. We provide vision therapy programs that will help your children to see the world at its very best.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[In the DreamWorks Movie Monsters Inc., Mike Wazowski is a lovable and laughable monster with one big eye. Unfortunately for Mike, in the real world he would never enjoy the capability of binocular vision. Interestingly, having two eyes isn’t enough for binocular vision to occur.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>573</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-06-20 21:25:18</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-06-20 21:25:18</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>two-eyes-are-better-than-one-the-importance-of-binocular-vision</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Amblyopia and Age: It Is Never Too Late</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=586</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2013 09:00:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=586</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[We once thought the earth was flat. We also never believed man could fly to the moon or that the information from thousands of books could fit into a device as small as an e-reader. Similarly, we once thought only very young children could be treated for amblyopia. <!--more-->

Today, we know that all of those statements are false. Older children, as well as adults, can be successfully treated. Not only can, but should. Early in the evolution of vision therapy as a medical field, the part of the brain responsible for vision was believed to have a short window of development. That window was believed to slam shut a few short years into childhood.

Fast forward a few decades, and research proved us wrong. The brain, as it turns out, is much more plastic than we originally thought, and it is able to follow a program to retrain the neurological-optical pathways, minimizing vision disorders, or even completely eliminating them, not just for young children, but for older children and even adults.

While it is easier for a young child to benefit from such therapy, a patient and dedicated older child or adult can gain much from the process, bumping up vision to read more quickly and with fewer symptoms of eyestrain such as headaches and blurred vision. Improving the way the eyes work together also restores binocular vision, an important factor in depth perception and coordination. 

Patients who have been told that they are too old should schedule an exam with an experienced developmental optometrist like Dr. Tod Davis. Dr. Davis and the staff at Dr. Tod Davis Developmental Optometry and Vision Therapy Services have been providing expert vision therapy programs for eastern Virginia residents for more than three decades. At our office, you are never too old to improve your vision. ]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[While it is easier for a young child to benefit from such therapy, a patient and dedicated older child or adult can gain much from the process, bumping up vision to read more quickly and with fewer symptoms of eyestrain such as headaches and blurred vision. Improving the way the eyes work together also restores binocular vision, an important factor in depth perception and coordination. ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>586</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-06-27 09:00:03</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-06-27 09:00:03</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>amblyopia-and-age-it-is-never-too-late</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Test Scores Dip When Vision Disorders Rule</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=589</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2013 09:00:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=589</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Some people thrive in a test environment. Others might be a little nervous, concerned about a particular subject they struggle with. Kids with vision disorders, however, really get double-teamed when standardized testing season comes around.<!--more-->

Undetected vision disorders can rob many students of their rightful test scores, as they fight to keep words on the page that jump and dissolve before their very eyes. Almost one in five students has an undetected vision disorder that makes reading harder than it should be due to eye teaming problems.

Students with vision disorders might be apprehensive about reading tasks all the time, but when the calendar rolls around for the big test, the one that compares them to everyone else, the pressure is on, aggravating their symptoms even further.

If eye teaming is not a struggle, or if processing errors add to the challenge, kids have difficulty tracking from line to line, as well as focusing on individual words and letters. They may complain of headaches and rub their eyes, giving that classic head tilt of confusion. Worse yet, the longer and harder they work, the more evasive the tasks become, further reducing their ability to do well in testing.

Many undetected vision problems have good solutions just waiting to be applied. Experts in vision therapy, like Dr. Tod Davis, are trained to diagnose and treat many of the disorders that inaccurately label students as lazy or not very smart. At Dr. Tod Davis Developmental Optometry and Vision Therapy Services, we believe every child deserves to perform up to their potential. Scheduling an exam for a vision assessment can restore your child’s confidence in his or her abilities through a program of vision therapy designed just for them. 
]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Undetected vision disorders can rob many students of their rightful test scores, as they fight to keep words on the page that jump and dissolve before their very eyes. Almost one in five students has an undetected vision disorder that makes reading harder than it should be due to eye teaming problems.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>589</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-07-04 09:00:28</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-07-04 09:00:28</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>test-scores-dip-when-vision-disorders-rule-dr-davis</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Reversal Frequency: Minding Your P’s and Q’s</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=593</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2013 09:00:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=593</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[As a young child learns to read and write, reversing or transposing a letter here or there is an expected mistake. If those reversals continue past the age of 8, however, there may be an issue with what is known as reversal frequency: mistaking a b for a d, or a p for a q. <!--more-->

Testing for letter and number reversals can be accomplished with the Gardner Reversals Test. The Gardner test differentiates between types of reversals, further identifying a patient with dysponesia, dyseidesia, or dysnemkinesia. 

Dysphonetics have difficulty integrating letters with sounds, and thus have a hard time sounding out words. Dyseidetics can sound out words, but have trouble with sequencing and find it tough to read an entire word at a time. Dysnemkinesics exhibit high reversal rates due to poor memory and motor skills.

While the dyslexic brain processes things differently, with early detection and treatment, significant progress can be made with a combination of vision therapy strategies and intervention. Beginning treatment as early as possible will help keep patients at peer levels in academic achievement and keep self-esteem high. Older patients, however, should not be discouraged from seeking treatment, as progress can be made at any age.

It is important to note that even developmental optometrists do not treat reading and learning disorders. That is something best managed by learning specialists in the field. Vision therapy, however, can provide an important piece of a multidisciplinary approach to improving academic performance in dyslexic individuals. 

If you feel your child may have a problem with reversal frequency, testing by a developmental optometrist such as Dr. Tod Davis can provide important information to help you decide on a next step. The staff at Dr. Tod Davis Developmental Optometry and Vision Therapy Services is trained to diagnose and work with patients that have a wide variety of vision disorders. They specialize in tailoring programs to the individual for maximum progress and satisfaction.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[While the dyslexic brain processes things differently, with early detection and treatment, significant progress can be made with a combination of vision therapy strategies and intervention. Beginning treatment as early as possible will help keep patients at peer levels in academic achievement and keep self-esteem high. Older patients, however, should not be discouraged from seeking treatment, as progress can be made at any age.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>593</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-07-18 09:00:52</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-07-18 09:00:52</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>reversal-frequency-minding-your-p%e2%80%99s-and-q%e2%80%99s-dr-davis</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Convergence Insufficiency: Sharpen Skills with Vision Therapy</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=595</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2013 09:00:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=595</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Some vision disorders are harder to diagnose than others. Convergence insufficiency, or the ability to sustain a focus on a letter or word, can be tricky. When children are just learning to read, things seem to go well at the beginning of a reading session, but deteriorate as the session continues. They can focus quickly but cannot sustain the focus and then begin to fail to recognize letters or make sense of words. Makes sense. If you cannot focus, it is very hard to read.<!--more-->

Reading requires pulling your eyes in, or converging them, to a focal point a short distance away. Looking up lets your eyes relax, allowing them to diverge at a distance far off on the horizon. Contracting muscles for convergence at close distances takes practice and work, yet still, some children are simply unable to sustain that close focus for long, experiencing convergence insufficiency. If they are unable to converge at all, then the more severe condition of convergence inability is at hand. 

Both convergence insufficiency and convergence inability are vision disorders that can be treated with vision therapy. Normally developed as a child begins to crawl, the convergence distance changed and encouraged development of the skill every time he or she raised up and gazed around or looked down at the floor. Further development happened on the playground equipment, reaching for bars, ropes and stairs. 

If a child went from crawling to walking too quickly, or if they weren’t allowed the opportunity to exercise their physical skills on a playground often enough, they may have not fully developed these skills. There is also a genetic component, with vision disorders having a tendency to run in families. 

Regardless of the reason, a solid program of vision therapy, designed by an experienced developmental optometrist like Dr. Tod Davis at Dr. Tod Davis Developmental Optometry and Vision Therapy Services, can teach your child to develop proper convergence skills. Don’t suffer through convergence issues that can be corrected. Put Dr. Davis and his team to work and get your child reaching for his or her full potential.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Both convergence insufficiency and convergence inability are vision disorders that can be treated with vision therapy. Normally developed as a child begins to crawl, the convergence distance changed and encouraged development of the skill every time he or she raised up and gazed around or looked down at the floor. Further development happened on the playground equipment, reaching for bars, ropes and stairs. ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>595</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-07-25 09:00:10</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-07-25 09:00:10</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>convergence-insufficiency-sharpen-skills-with-vision-therapy-dr-davis</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>“What Does This Have To Do With My Vision!?” Movement and Vision Therapy</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=606</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2013 20:00:40 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=606</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Kids-moving.jpg"><img src="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Kids-moving.jpg" alt="" title="Kids moving" width="300" height="200" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-607" /></a>

In Vision Therapy we often hear the following question from patients or their loved ones: “What does this have to do with vision?” They are referring to physical activities like building core muscle tone and integrating primitive reflexes. Understanding how movement effects on our developing vision is important to understanding the developmental foundation of Vision Therapy.

Primitive reflexes are automated movements that are not initiated by conscious thought. They are a part of a child's pre and postnatal development. Primitive reflexes are necessary for initiating specific movements during delivery and afterward for infant safety and survival. This is why they have been referred to as "primitive" reflexes. In ideal infant and child development the primitive reflexes fade, or become integrated, as the child develops more sophisticated sensory and motor functions. However, in some children they do not become integrated and persist.

<a href="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Catch.jpg"><img src="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Catch.jpg" alt="" title="Catch" width="193" height="300" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-608" /></a>

Imagine a five year old child trying to catch a rubber ball and consistently missing the ball by trying to wrap their arms around it rather than using their hands to catch it. This often happens in children who do not integrate a reflex called symmetrical tonic neck reflex (STNR). This particular reflex is useful to an infant up to eight months and aides in crawling, a major developmental milestone. In this scenario, the reflex which initially aided in the child’s development has become a road block to optimal development by preventing the intended movements of the child when trying to catch a ball.

Vision develops in predictable stages and is predicated on a child’s movements; whether reaching for an object or moving their entire body in a given direction. It begins with the child putting things to his or her mouth to determine size, shape and density. As the child matures he or she will begin to use their hands to explore objects and the environment. Eventually the experiences with the mouth and hands will equip a child with a substantial understanding of their environment and the objects in it so that they can rely on the use of their eyes to determine size, shape, location and spatial awareness of things.

Physical and cognitive development is based on our ability to move in our environments and experience and manipulate objects and information. Anything preventing the child’s conscious or intended movements also prevents that child’s exploration and eventual understanding of their environment. Unconscious movement patterns delay and sometimes prevent physical and cognitive development, which inhibits normal development of the visual system and leads to many learning challenges.

Many of the problems associated with retained primitive reflexes or limited movement during key stages of development include poor balance, low muscle tone, poor body awareness, poor eye movement control, orientation, and reduced cognitive abilities. This is why the building of core muscle strength is a crucial part of vision therapy activities. Abdominal crunches not only build a foundation for good muscle tone, but an improved ability to move one’s body and the development of vision.

Fortunately, primitive reflexes can be integrated through specific repetitive movement patterns. Vision Therapy includes activities to incorporate primitive reflexes and improve a child’s conscious movement in their environment. These therapeutic activities are designed to either counter or mimic the reflexive movement with an emphasis on conscious muscular control by the child. Therapy involves the repetition of these specific movements to guide the child through basic physical skills (body mechanics) to body awareness (left and right, upper and lower body, and coordination). These therapies result in the child’s conscious awareness and control of their body.  The integration of the primitive reflexes leads to intended motor control and increased visual development.

If you have questions or concerns related to primitive reflexes and their effect on your child’s visual development contact a developmental optometrists, like Dr. Todd Davis and Dr. Amy Carlyle, Developmental Optometry - Vision Therapy. After a thorough screening and diagnosis they can craft a vision therapy program specifically designed to cultivate the most optimal and efficient visual system in your child, providing a more certain futur]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[In Vision Therapy we often hear the following question from patients or their loved ones: “What does this have to do with vision?” They are referring to physical activities like building core muscle tone and integrating primitive reflexes. Understanding how movement effects on our developing vision is important to understanding the developmental foundation of Vision Therapy.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>606</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-07-16 20:00:40</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-07-16 20:00:40</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>%e2%80%9cwhat-does-this-have-to-do-with-my-vision%e2%80%9d-movement-and-vision-therapy</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Would You Look at That! Fixation, Fixation, Fixation</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=612</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2013 17:29:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=612</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Right now as you read these words your eyes are fixating at successive points along the screen. Visual fixation is the neuromuscular aiming of the eyes at a specific point in space. You can easily understand the need for fixation when you imagine someone involved in detailed work, like threading a needle, or sporting activities, such as throwing a baseball. According to many researchers fixation is determined by three basic factors; salience of the visual stimulus, memory or importance of the stimulus, and the nature of an activity we are engaged in.
<a href="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/thCAXVEHTK1.jpg"><img src="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/thCAXVEHTK1.jpg" alt="" title="thCAXVEHTK" width="292" height="300" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-619" /></a>Whether we fixate on one thing or another can depend on the salience of the stimulus, or how prominent something is in the environment (like bright balloons). Color, illumination, contrast, and patterns determine how people perceive the prominence of something in their environment. Advertisers take advantage of this by presenting consumer products in a very particular way so that their product is prominently displayed with dramatic lighting and surrounding colors.
Have you ever stared at something unknowingly for a several seconds until you realized the thing that caught your attention had actually triggered a memory or sequence of memories? Before you know it, you’ve been staring at it for several minutes. Recognition, memory and familiarity are prominent aspects of fixation. How well we fixate on an object or scene is dependent on if the object or aspects of the scene are interesting, contrasting, or familiar to us in some way.
Clearly some tasks are more important than others; driving versus watching television for instance. Safe driving requires one’s full attention and will demand fixation on the road ahead or other cars nearby. This is why the use of electronic devices, like a phone or music player, while driving is so dangerous. Watching television can be a very passive activity and does not require we completely fixate on what’s happening. The nature of a particular task can override what we fixate on whether something in our environment has salience, prominence or is memorable or familiar to us. Task fixation is one example of how we control what we fixate on and why.
<a href="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/thCAGOD6ZI.jpg"><img src="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/thCAGOD6ZI.jpg" alt="" title="thCAGOD6ZI" width="300" height="168" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-621" /></a>
Vision related challenges like convergence insufficiency; amblyopia and/or strabismus (the turning of an eye in or out) limit or prevent the eyes to aim at a specific point in space. Some studies suggest that this can affect twenty percent of children with learning related issues. Short and long term memory can also be affected by vision related disorders. If you have questions or concerns about fixation or any of the vision related issues noted in this article contact a developmental optometrists, like Dr. Todd Davis and Dr. Amy Carlyle, Developmental Optometry - Vision Therapy. After a detailed screening and diagnosis they can design a vision therapy program specifically suited to develop the most optimal and efficient visual system for you or your child.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Right now as you read these words your eyes are fixating at successive points along the screen. Visual fixation is the neuromuscular aiming of the eyes at a specific point in space. You can easily understand the need for fixation when you imagine someone involved in detailed work, like threading a needle, or sporting activities, such as throwing a baseball. ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>612</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-08-05 17:29:45</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-08-05 17:29:45</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>would-you-look-at-that-fixation-fixation-fixation</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Reading Fun to Reading Nightmares</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=629</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2013 19:13:13 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=629</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Reading-Difficulty.jpg"><img src="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Reading-Difficulty.jpg" alt="" title="Reading Difficulty" width="232" height="300" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-631" /></a>

For many, first grade is the start of many years of fun and exciting discoveries; like playing sports or musical instruments, and learning to read. Reading for most children is a gateway to new information and a new understanding about the world around them. For many it is a fun and exciting adventure. For others it can be frustrating, lonely, disappointing, and confusing time, because words and numbers make no sense due to blurred vision or double-vision. Some of these children endure jokes and ridicule from peers over failure in the classroom. As well, they become defeated because they are unable to describe the problems they are facing. Many simply avoid reading or fight against it.

If you, or someone you know and love, falls into that second category, perhaps it is time for a thorough vision exam by a developmental optometrist. Many early reading problems can be associated with an undiscovered vision disorders, like convergence insufficiency or amblyiopia. Developmental Optometrists like Dr. Tod Davis are trained to recognize and treat vision problems with vision therapy. 

Vision problems can be treated through lenses, exercises, and other vision therapy activities, to improve binocular function. Vision therapy programs designed by developmental optometrists can provide strategies and skills that help students reach academic milestones that once seemed out of reach. We have seen hundreds of once poor performers turn into dynamic achievers with new found confidence and passion for learning.

Helping struggling students to achieve and succeed through vision therapy will not only improve academic progress, but will undoubtedly improve self image, a critical piece of the social scene in school. Early detection and treatment helps keep students aligned with peers, losing as little ground as possible. 

Scheduling an appointment with a good developmental optometrist that understands the challenges many children face, and that can design a vision therapy program to engage the student, improve the skills, and gain confidence, is a priceless gift. If you have questions about someone you know and love, and how to help them reach their potential, the staff at Dr. Tod Davis Developmental Optometry and Vision Therapy Services would love to provide some answers.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>629</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-08-22 19:13:13</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-08-22 19:13:13</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>reading-fun-to-reading-nightmares</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>From Flat to Phenomenal: 3D Film Seems to Cause Real Life Change</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=635</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2013 19:36:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=635</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Can a movie ticket change your life? It would seem so, at least for one movie fan. 

<a href="http://bsandrew.blogspot.co.uk/2012/03/how-hugo-gave-one-neuroscientist-gift_630.html">Dr. Bruce Bridgeman </a>and his wife walked into a movie theatre, picked up their 3D glasses and found a seat in preparation to view the 3D film Hugo. Donning the 3D glasses, Bridgeman, afflicted with the inability to process depth perception, was prepared only to eliminate the confusion of viewing a 3D film without filtration. Instead, the event left him nothing short of euphoric.

<a href="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/3D-Movie.jpg"><img src="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/3D-Movie.jpg" alt="" title="3D Movie" width="300" height="213" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-636" /></a>

The film sparked a level of depth perception in his viewing that he had never experienced, delivering a huge dose of stereo vision as trees, lamp posts, and cars jumped out at him for the first time. Even after exiting the theatre, Bridgeman continued to see in 3D, an effort that eluded him for nearly all of his life. 

While readers should use caution in assuming a 3D film can fix the flat vision of a person lacking stereopsis, Bridgeman’s experience is proof of the elasticity of the neurological-visual systems in processing images. Some feel the highly exaggerated 3D film produced just the right stimulus to reawaken neuro-visual pathways, in effect jump-starting Bridgeman’s depth perception.

Bridgeman was also well into his adult life, adding to the impressive elasticity of the brain with regard to recharging visual pathways outside of the childhood window once thought to be the only effective time period for treatment.

Drs. Tod Davis and Amy Carlyle, and the staff at Developmental Optometry and Vision Therapy Services are eager to help patients develop their vision to see the world at its best. If you, or someone you love, is experiencing less than adequate vision, please consider Dr. Davis your intelligent, experienced resource with answers to your vision questions. 
]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>635</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-08-26 19:36:57</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-08-26 19:36:57</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>from-flat-to-phenomenal-3d-film-seems-to-cause-real-life-change</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>The Eye’s Not Lazy: Amblyopia Explained</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=639</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2013 20:24:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=639</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[The term "lazy eye" is a loosely used medical term that intones an older view of what is the most common cause of visual impairment in U.S. children, approximately five percent have it. The actual medical term is Amblyopia.  It’s not an eye problem, it’s a problem where the brain ignores visual images from one eye due to a variety of vision disorders that cause double or blurred vision. The eye is not “lazy”, the brain is simply eliminating conflicting visual information by ignoring one of the images.

To look through a pair of amblyopic eyes is challenging. Things are unclear. Shadows are hazy. Highlights and details are gone and colors are less vivid. One amblyopic patient describes looking at the world through her amblyopic eye is like holding her breath, or not scratching an itch, desperately wanting to open the stronger eye to let it take over.

Tracking while reading can be very difficult with an amblyopic eye, as lines of type become wavy and even develop motion, causing the reader to lose track of progress. It also makes things go pretty slow, struggling to pay attention and interpret each and every word as it dances and fades.

When letters appear in a crowd, such as a word-find puzzle, people with amblyopia have difficulty seeing individual letters as opposed to one big mass of marks. Letters in the middle of the puzzle blur and blend into each other. Identifying letters becomes as difficult as counting grains of rice spilled on the floor from a standing position. Hard to determine which grains you’ve already counted, right? 

There is a good amblyopia simulation for those wanting to experience what an amblyopia sufferer might experience. In a normally-lit room, put a patch on one eye, or just cover it with your hand, for two to five minutes. Then, either have someone turn the lights out, or move to a darkened room and uncover your eye. The covered eye has adjusted to the dark conditions, and will see pretty well, but the uncovered eye will not see very well, experiencing a disadvantage. That disadvantage of that uncovered eye moving from light into dark is similar to the disadvantage experienced with amblyopia. Try it and “see” for yourself.

Drs. Tod Davis and Amy Carlyle would like to remind readers that there is help for those with vision disorders like amblyopia. Their staff at Dr. Tod Davis Developmental Optometry and Vision Therapy Services can work with you to develop a program that will have you seeing the world at its very best.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>639</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-09-04 20:24:27</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-09-04 20:24:27</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>the-eye%e2%80%99s-not-lazy-amblyopia-explained</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>How to Give Vision Therapy a “Go” When Insurance Says “No”</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=642</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2013 17:29:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=642</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/Traffic-Light.jpg"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-643" title="Traffic Light" src="http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/Traffic-Light.jpg" alt="" width="217" height="300" /></a>

Insurance can often be helpful, but it can also be confusing and frustrating. When sorting out the details of coverage for vision therapy, the route to successful insurance conclusions is pretty simple if you know what questions to ask, and figure out a plan with input from your vision care provider and your insurance agent.

Most patients will find that initial comprehensive exams are covered. Many policies will also cover an additional exam to evaluate a patient’s visual information processing to determine an appropriate treatment program. That doesn’t mean yours will, however, so please make sure to check with your agent regarding your particular policy.

Some insurance companies offer coverage for vision therapy, but just because they offer it does not mean that your policy includes it. A conversation with your insurance agent or workplace HR department can help you determine what will be covered. Toward that end, there are some important questions to ask that will help in the planning stages of therapy:

•	Ask if vision therapy is covered, sometimes referred to as orthoptics in the insurance industry. If coverage is a part of your plan, it might also be smart to ask if there is an annual limit, or lifetime limit, for coverage. Note that vision therapy is most often applied to a medical policy as opposed to a vision policy.
•	Ask which CPT insurance billing codes are covered under your policy with regard to vision therapy. Most therapy providers use code numbers 99203, 99204, and 92015 to bill for an initial vision exam of between 1 – 2 hours. For assessing a patient’s visual information processing, and a 2-hour appointment, commonly used CPT codes may include 96111, 96116, or 92060. Therapy sessions lasting up to an hour often use the code number 92065. For progress visits, codes 99213, 92060, 96111, and 96116 are commonly cited.
•	Ask if therapy visits must be pre-authorized in order to be covered, and make sure you understand and comply with the requirements.
•	Ask what the out of network deductible will be if your provider is not a recognized provider with your insurance company.
•	Ask what your coinsurance payment will be once your deductible is met.
•	Ask how long it will take for the insurance company to reimburse you.

If you are contributing to a flexible spending health care account, you may be able to apply funds from that account toward vision therapy. Also, should any claims be denied, you have the right to file an appeal, which can resolve in favor of the patient.

The staff at Drs. Tod Davis and Amy Carlyle Developmental Optometry and Vision Therapy Services is there to help patients navigate not only the highly specialized treatment programs and options, but also the sometimes challenging world of insurance codes and processing. Rest assured that Drs. Tod Davis and Amy Carlyle, supported by a superior professional staff, is invested in the wellbeing of their patients, and will go the extra mile to ensure patients receive the treatments they need. Visit www.davisvisiontherapy.com today for more information.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Insurance can often be helpful, but it can also be confusing and frustrating. When sorting out the details of coverage for vision therapy, the route to successful insurance conclusions is pretty simple if you know what questions to ask, and figure out a plan with input from your vision care provider and your insurance agent.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>642</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-09-06 17:29:10</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-09-06 17:29:10</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>closed</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>how-to-give-vision-therapy-a-%e2%80%9cgo%e2%80%9d-when-insurance-says-%e2%80%9cno%e2%80%9d</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Diabetes &amp; Your Eyes</title>
		<link>http://www.geademo2.com/dandy/davisvisiontherapy/blog/?p=647</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2013 08:01:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.davisvisiontherapy.com/blog/?p=647</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img alt="" src="http://davisvisiontherapy.com.previewdns.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/Diabetes11.png" title="Diabetes" class="alignnone" width="652" height="306" style="border:1px solid #cdcdcd;" />
Diabetes is a chronic disease that prevents your body from making or using insulin, which in turn leads to increased sugar levels in your bloodstream, known as high blood sugar.

Diabetes and its complications can affect many parts of the eye. Diabetes can cause changes in farsightedness, nearsightedness, and premature presbyopia (the inability to focus on objects close by). It can result in glaucoma, cataracts, and paralysis of the nerves that control the eye muscles. Visual symptoms of diabetes include occasional double vision, loss of visual field, flashes and floaters within the eyes. Sometimes these early signs of diabetes are first detected in a thorough examination performed by our office staff. The most serious eye problem associated with diabetes is diabetic retinopathy.

Diabetic retinopathy occurs when blood vessels in the retina change, resulting in blood leakage, the growth of new blood vessels and other changes. If diabetic retinopathy is left untreated, blindness can result.

<strong>Can vision loss from diabetes be prevented?</strong>

Yes, in a routine eye examination, the staff at Dr. Tod Davis and Amy Carlyle Developmental Optometry and Vision Therapy Services can diagnose potential vision threatening changes in your eye that may be treated to prevent blindness. However, once damage has occurred, the effects are usually permanent. It is important to control your diabetes as much as possible to minimize your risk of developing retinopathy.
]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>647</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-10-06 08:01:02</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-10-06 08:01:02</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>closed</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>diabetes-your-eyes</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
	</item>
</channel>
</rss>
